<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The famous and renowned history of Sir Bevis of Southampton giving an account of his birth, education, heroick exploits, and enterprises, his fights with giants, monsters, wild-beasts, and armies, his conquering kings and kingdoms, his love and marriage, fortunes and misfortunes, and many other famous and memorable things and actions, worthy of wonder : with the adventures of other knights, kings and princes, exceeding pleasant and delightful to read.</title>
            <title>Beves of Hamtoun (Romance)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22064</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12298786</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12298786</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40838)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 626:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The famous and renowned history of Sir Bevis of Southampton giving an account of his birth, education, heroick exploits, and enterprises, his fights with giants, monsters, wild-beasts, and armies, his conquering kings and kingdoms, his love and marriage, fortunes and misfortunes, and many other famous and memorable things and actions, worthy of wonder : with the adventures of other knights, kings and princes, exceeding pleasant and delightful to read.</title>
                  <title>Beves of Hamtoun (Romance)</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78, [2] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Thackeray ..., and J. Deacon ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A prose version.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59120:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59120:1"/>
            <p>The Famous and Renowned HISTORY OF <hi rend="blackletterType">Sir Bevis</hi> of <hi rend="blackletterType">Southampton</hi> GIVING An Account of his Birth, Education, Heroick Exploits, and Enterpriſes, his Fights with Giants, Monſters, Wild-Beaſts and Armies, his Conquering Kings and Kingdoms, his Love and Marriage, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes and Misfortunes, and many other Famous and Memorable Things and Actions, worthy of Wonder; With the Adventures of other Knights, Kings and Princes, exceeding pleaſant and delightful to Read.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>W. Thackeray</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Duck-Lane,</hi> and <hi>J. Deacon</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Gilt-Spur-ſtreet,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59120:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59120:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Here preſent you with the pleaſant Hiſtory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and Renowned Knight, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> a Man for his Virtue and Valour, highly eſteemed throughout the World: In whoſe many Actions and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Achievements, you will find things that may reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſurmout an ordinary credit, however in peruſing them, you may plainly perceive the difference between Elder times and theſe we live in, which are too much divovled into ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminacy, and pleaſe your ſelf in conſulting the many rare Adventures of ſuch, as gave themſelves up to the practice of Arms and Love, which being mingled in their many excellencies, appear as beautiful and gay as a Bed of Roſes and Lillies, in their bluſhing Glory and innocent Candure, and as the noble Enterprizes of others have ſtirred up the Spirits of ſuch as read them, to an illuſtrous imitation of what is truly great, and held in the higheſt eſteem: So paſt all peradventure, what is here laid down, will not come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the moſt exaulted Actions of Heroes, ſet forth to the beſt advantage, either in Love or Arms, thoſe two Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies that adorn mankind; for here you will find our
<pb facs="tcp:59120:3"/> Champion, though early cruſhed by the adverſe hand of Fortune, making his way to Glory, before he could aſpire to Manhood, cutting it by Dint of Valour and Heroick Conduct from a dejected ſtate by degrees, till he mounts to the higheſt pinacle of Honour, in reſcuing the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, deſtroying Monſters and Tyrants, gaining Kingdoms, and converting Infidels to the Chriſtian Faith, obleiging by his Affability and excellent parts Queens and Princeſſes, to lay their Diadems and Grandure at his feet, and doing ſuch things as have amazed Mankind. Therefore for the honour of our Country, of which he has ſo well deſerved, let his Memory live in the thoughts of every true Engliſh Man, and be to them a pattern of Heroick Virtue, that by imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating him, they may raiſe the very name of the Britiſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as formerly it was, to be the Terror of the World, which is the wiſh,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Reader,</salute> 
               <signed>Of your moſt Humble Servant <hi>S. J.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59120:3"/>
            <head>THE Famous and Renowned HISTORY OF Sir BEVIS of SOUTHAMPTON.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Guy</hi> Earl of <hi rend="blackletterType">Southampton,</hi> having married a fair Lady, had by her Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis;</hi> and how ſhe afterward cauſed her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to be treacherouſly ſlain in the Forreſt, and married the Knight that ſlew him &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN the days, when <hi>England</hi> was more immediately renowned, for the famous and valiant Atchievements of other Knightsland Warlike, Champions, whoſe greht Actions and Heroick Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes were loudly trumped by Faine, in each part of the World. There dwelt at the antient and celebrated Town of <hi>Southampton,</hi> a Knight called Sir <hi>Guy,</hi> who in his Travels and ſearch of Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures through the Countries of <hi>Flanders, France, Almain, Cicile, De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rk, Gaſcom, Hungary, Culabria, Burgundy, Poland, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy, Maine, Turkey, Eaſtland, Norway, Picardy, Scotland, Lumbardy, &amp;c.</hi> ſignalized his Valour in the Courrs of divers great Princes at Tilt, Tournament, and many mortal Combats, ever ſtriving to right the injured, and ſuch as ſuffered wrong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their too powerful oppreſſors, and having ſpent his younger days in the exerciſe of Arms abroad, every where gaining a high eſteem, at length Age rendring him unfit for great exploits, he reſolved to give up the remainder of his lift to a more ſetled ſtate in his own Country, and thereupon returning loaden with Lawrels won with infinite hazzard and danger, as alſo with the Preſents and Favour of Emperors, Kings and Princes: he at length ſetled in the Town of <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> the place of his birth, but long he had not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d there in all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary conrentment, and adicted himſelf to works of Piery and Charity, before King <hi>Edgar</hi> having been ſufficiently informed of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59120:4"/> his high deſerts, made him Earl of that place, and calling him to Court, appointed him his Steward, or rather Vice-Roy, in which place he ſo well diſcharged his truſt, in doing Iuſtice to every man, countenancing virtue and ſuppreſſing vice, that he gained an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal commendation: and being now where he had dayly the ſight of a great many beautiful Ladies he bethought himſelf of Marriage, that ſo he might leave behind him an Heir to poſſeſs his great Wealth and Virtues; and caſting his Eyes upon the Daughter of the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who was then in the Engliſh Court, he ſo prevailed with the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> by the means of King <hi>Edgar</hi> his Maſter, that he ſoon had her to Wife; though this Marriage, by reaſon ſhe had ſecretly placed her affections before, on the Emperor of <hi>Edmain's</hi> Brother, prove altogether unhappy to the Earl, as in the ſequel will appear.</p>
               <p>The Marriage Rites being performed with great ſplendor, and graced with the preſence of the two Kings, and the Nobles of both Kingdoms: In proceſs of time the Lady brought him forth a Son, whom they agreed to be called <hi>Bevis,</hi> afterward known, or common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called by the name of <hi>Bevis</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> whoſe Knighly Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and noble Actions are the ſubject of this pleaſant and renowned Hiſtory. However the Lady ſtill keeping up her affections for her former Lover, whoſe name was Sir <hi>Murdure,</hi> by reaſon he was ſprightly, young and active, and Sir <hi>Guy</hi> her Husband on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, being much in years, and not ſo apt as ſhe required to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie her youthful deſires, adicting himſelf rather to his Devotion, and to obtain a pardon for Sins by a thorough Repentance; which made her begin to conclude her ſelf unhappy in this Marriage, and wiſhed ſhe had been given to him ſhe more dearly affected, ſuffering her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content dayly to increaſe, till at length growing from a diſlike to a hatred of her Lord: She reſolved to be rid of him, and thereupon ſent a truſty Meſſenger to the Emperors Court, to acquaint Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> of her great Love to him, and the diſlike ſhe had of her Husband, aſſuring him, that he ever had her heart and entire affection, though forced by the commands of a Father, ſhe had given her hand to another, which made her life uneaſie, and that now there remained no way to render it comfortable, but by removing the man, who hindred the mingling of their mutual Paſſions and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and that to compleat both their happyneſſeſs, he would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to kill him, ſhe would ſo contrive it as to give him the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59120:4"/> by perſwading him with a ſlender Train to hunt the Boa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the great Forreſt then adjoyning to the Town of <hi>Southampton,</hi> and there with a ſtrong well arm'd Guard might effect it at leaſure.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>At the wicked propoſal of the Lady, Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> ſtood for a while mute and much amazed, but at laſt, the great Love he had ever born to ſo beautiful a Woman, as was the Counteſs, and not knowing any other means to enjoy her, whom he now underſtood was as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to yield, as he to intreat, conſented to obey her pleaſure, telling the Meſſenger, that on the firſt day of <hi>May</hi> he would arrive in <hi>England</hi> with a Company of well arm'd men, ſufficient to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what ſhe deſired, and that done, lay himſelf at her feet, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with a gallant Steed, he diſmiſſed him.</p>
               <p>The Lady having heard the anſwer of the Knight, was much pleaſed thereat, and then upon feigning her ſelf ill at eaſe, ſhe ſent a Servant to her Husband, to advertiſe him of it, who immediately came to her, and with much love and tenderneſs enquired into the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59120:5"/> cauſe of her grief, who with a ſigh replyed, that ſhe was ignorant of it, unleſs it proceeded from a longing mind ſhe had for to taſte the fleſh of a Wild-Boar, and when he demanded where one might be found, and it ſhould at any rate be taken, ſhe ſaid ſhe had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>med, that a Boar had a long time haunted the neighbouring For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, but taking her Lord about the Neck, ſhe with a diſſembling k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> entreated him not to hazard himſelf againſt ſo dangerous a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for her occaſion, and rather than it ſhould be, to ſuffer any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience; however as ſhe wiſhed, he would not decline it, but cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for his Horſe, his Launce and Sword, with only two of his Servants, he betook himſelf to the Forreſt in ſearch of the Wild-Boar, but there he had not long been, but Sir <hi>Murdure,</hi> who had placed himſelf in ambuſh, burſt out upon him, and reviling him by the name perfidious Traitor, for bereaving him of his Miſtriſs, whom he had a long time loved, and for whom he had ſuffered ſo much, he told him though he now enjoyed her, it ſhould not be long for that both he and his Son ſhould dy.</p>
               <p>The Earl thus ſurprized, called to his Servants to advertize them of the Treachery, ſaying, at the ſame time, he would however in his own right, defend himſelf to the utmoſt, when having his Launce in his Reſt, he run againſt Sir <hi>Murdure,</hi> and hitting him full, bore hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the ground, and thereupon drew his Sword, and being about to ſtrike off his Head, he cryed out to his Fellows for reſcue who came ſo furiouſly upon the Earl, that he was forced to deſiſt, and defend himſelf, when having ſlain divers of them, they being twenty in number, and wanting his Armour, through the many wounds he had received, he was at laſt obleiged to forſake his Horſe, who was likewiſe ſorely wounded, and about to fall under him, yet he fought couragiouſly, but his Servants being ſlain, and he incloſed on every ſide, fainting through loſs of blood, he ſaid to Sir <hi>Murdure,</hi> for the honour of Knighthood and true Chivalry at this time ſpare my life, having me unarmed, at ſo great a diſadvantage, and I promiſe, old as I am to arm my ſelf, and meet you and your Train, and if you kill me then, I ſhall freely pardon you my death; but they would in no wiſe hearken to him, for whilſt he was about to proceed, in requiring his life to be ſpared, Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> with his Spear run him through the body, and thoſe that accompanied him gave him ſo many wounds that he dyed on the place; after which the unworthy Knight cut off his Head, and ſent it by one of his Servants, as a Preſent to the Lady,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59120:5"/> aſſuring her he would be with her that night: whereat ſhe appeared much overjoyed, and received it with great ſatisfaction; promiſing to be at his Devotion: And accordingly he ſoon after Wedded the Lady, it being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore given out that her Husband the Earl was Murthered by a Band of Robbers.</p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Bevis</hi> was delivered to Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> to be put to Death, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Mother and Step-Father. The means by which he was ſaved; and how, in the Habit of a Shepherd, he kept Sheep, and in ſome part revenged his Fathers Murther. How he left the Land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEvis</hi> hearing of his Fathers Death, greatly lamented it; and being of ſome years of underſtanding, ſoon perceived by his Mothers car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and whiſperings amongſt the Servants, as alſo Sir <hi>Murdure</hi>'s high
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59120:6"/> Entertainment, that ſhe had not the leaſt hand in the contriving it, and thereupon took the freedom to tell her his thoughts, in ſuch bitter Language as incenſed her grievouſly to chaſtize him; but finding him obſtinate and fearing one day he would not only diſcover but revenge his Fathers Death, ſhe reſolved to make him away, and thereupon conſulted with one Sir <hi>Sabre,</hi> over whom ſhe had a great power and influence, to deſtroy him; who accordingly promiſed it, without any intention to perform it. Wherefore, that he might keep notwithſtanding in her good opinion, he took him home to his Houſe, pretending it required great Privacy; and there he informed the Youth of the danger he was in, and how that he had it in charge to kill him, but on the contrary was reſolved to conceal him, till ſuch time he was able to bear Arms for the recovery of his Fathers Eſtate: adding, That he, for the Friendſhip he bore Sir <hi>Guy,</hi> would then aſſiſt him with a power ſufficient to effect it, and whilſt he had an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, to convey him to his other Vncle, who was an Earl in <hi>Wales,</hi> he ſhould keep his Sheep upon the neighbouring Downs. At this <hi>Bevis</hi> wept for anger, to be ſo uſed by his cruel Mother whilſt his Fathers Murtherer revelled in his Palace, yet concealed it as well as he could, in hopes, one day to be revenged, condeſcending to have his rich Cloaths changed for thoſe of a Shepherd, all tattered and ragged; and in that diſguiſe drove forth Sir <hi>Sabre</hi>'s Sheep each morning, warily guarding them upon the flowry Plains, and chearing himſelf with his Pipe of Reeds, wearing a Shepherds Scrip, and carrying in his hand a Crook, and at Even he brought them home again, contenting himſelf with courſe Fare and a homely Lodging; till coming to the Age of ſixteen years he exerciſed the firſt proof of his valour upon a fierce and cruel Wolf, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come into thoſe parts, that deſtroyed not only many Sheep and tender Lambs but killed ſome of the Shepherds that ſought to defend them, and put others to the ſlight; and thinking to do the like to <hi>Bevis,</hi> who was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Field, met him open-mouth'd, but <hi>Bevis</hi> with the end of his Crook ſtruck him ſo full on the head as he came at him, that he fell to the Ground; when cloſing with him, he with much eaſe ſtrangled him with main force, which made the Neighbouring Shepherds exceedingly rejoyce, and much praiſe the courage and reſolution of <hi>Bevis,</hi> who by this Act had delivered them from fear and danger. And ſoon after he began to ſhow his ſtrength, inſomuch that none were able to contend with him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Wreſtling, Running, Throwing the Bar, or at hard Blows, ſo that his Renown began by degrees to ſpread abroad, and many both lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and feared him.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59120:6"/>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bevis</hi> thinking himſelf partly revenged of his Father-in-law, went ſecretly to Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> and told him all that had paſſed, who was much
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59120:7"/> diſpleaſed thereat, ſaying, <hi>That it would ſoon be known who he was, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſelf muſt conſequently ſuffer for concealing him,</hi> Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he cauſed him to be hid in the Wood for ſome time, till he thought the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch might be over. Nor did his conjectures much fail him, for the Counteſs, after recovering from the Sound ſhe fell into, upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing her Husband ſlain, declared, that ſhe verily Believed it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Son <hi>Bevis,</hi> as well by his voice as a mark in his Face, that had tooke in diſguiſe to diſturb her Peace, vowing the deſtruction of Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> at he had not made him away: And thereupon, in a great rage, ſhe went attended with a Guard to his Houſe, and finding him there, charged him as falſe and faithleſs to his promiſe, threatning him with Tortur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and Death, for abuſing her Truſt: but he on the contrary, all edges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e had been obedient to her Commands, producing the Cloaths he had p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely dipped in the Blood of a Swine: however, ſo confident ſhe was of the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That he was not made away, that having rated and reviled him as long as ſhe pleaſed, without hearkning to any of his excuſes, charged two Knights to carry him to a Caſtle adjoyning to the Forreſt, and there Impriſon him till hers and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lords Pleaſure were father known.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bevis</hi> hearing of the misfortune of his Vncle, reſolved at the hazard of his life to ſet him at liberty: and with this reſolution, getting a Palmer's Gown, and arming himſelf under it with a truſty Sword, he went and knocked at the Gate, in which diſguiſe he had entrance, without being ſuſpected, and by main force having ſubdued the Keepers or Warders, he with an Iron Bar he found there, burſt in ſunder the Doors for more ſpeed, and finding Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> there in Chains, he ſet him forthwith at Liberty, and binding the Keepers in the ſame Chains left the Caſtle; yet knowing they would be narrowly ſought after, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> agreed to leave the Land in ſearch of Adventures, and Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> giving out that it was not <hi>Bevis,</hi> but an unknown Knight in diſguiſe, who had done the Miſchief, and wrought his deliverance; <hi>Bevis</hi> being to his knowledge certainly dead, his Poſſeſſions that had been taken from him were again reſtored, and he received into fovour.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59120:8"/>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> was ſhipwracked in a Storm, taken Priſoner and ſold to ſundry Merchants, who preſented him to the King of <hi>Armony,</hi> who kindly entertained him. How the fair Princeſs <hi rend="blackletterType">Ioſian</hi> fell in Love with him. And how he fought with and overcome ſixty <hi rend="blackletterType">Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razens,</hi> and was doomed to dye, and how delivered.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEvis</hi> having taken the Sea in a ſmall Bark, a great Tempeſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, almoſt as ſoon as it was put from Land, and continued with ſuch Fury, that all rule was loſt, and the Ship riding furiouſly before the Wind, beaten with Rain, Thunder, Lightning and the Waves of the Sea, neither Sun, Moon, nor Stars appearing for many days, they were at laſt driven into a ſtrong Haven in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, poſſeſſed by the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> where the Veſſel being broken on the Rocks,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59120:8"/> 
                  <hi>Bevis</hi> with ſome few got on ſhoar, but there, contrary to the Rules of Hoſpitality, they were encountered and taken Priſoners by a great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Infidels, who ſold them to the Merchants, bound for the Coaſt of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who preſented <hi>Bevis,</hi> as a very comely Perſonage, to the King of <hi>Armony,</hi> who then had to his Daughter a Princeſs exceeding fair and beautifull, adorned with all the rare perfections that make Women<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind tempting and deſirable, on whom <hi>Bevis</hi> fixing his Eyes, began to think he had never ſeen any ſo charming, her Eyes ſeemed like two Stars, her Forehead like poliſhed Alablaſter, her Cheeks out-did the Roſes, and her Lips and Teeth might compare with Rubies and Pearls, all her other parts being proportionably beautifull; but above all ſhe was poſſeſſed with a virtuous mind and courteous behaviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bevis</hi> being now in the Court of <hi>Armony,</hi> the King had great delight to ſee a Youth ſo comely, well ſet and ſtrong proportioned in his Limbs, every part of him expreſſing a more than manly form, and promiſing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſtrength; wherefore giving him words of comfort, he began to queſtion him about his Birth and Parentage, who freely told him that he was Son to <hi>Guy</hi> Earl of <hi>Southampton,</hi> and that his Father being treacherouſly ſlain by the conſent of his Mother, who likewiſe ſought his Life, he had betaken himſelf to travel, and being unfortunately ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoner, he had been ſold to thoſe Merchants who had preſented him to his Highneſs. Vpon this the King embraced him, and told him he was now more dear to him, as being the Son of Sir <hi>Guy,</hi> whoſe Fame had ſounded loud in thoſe parts, and his many noble Actions made his name immortal; however, grieving that the World had loſt ſo brave a Man by Treatchery, that could not have been overcome by fair force, conſtituted <hi>Bevis</hi> his great Chamberlain, committing to his care and charge Veſtures of Gold, Silver and Pearls, Diamonds and other precious ſtones and great riches in abundance, being wonderfully pleaſed, as often as his great Affairs would give him leiſure, to hold diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with him of many things, for <hi>Bevis</hi> was no ways ignorant of any Learning. And ſo it happened, that he had not long been in this place with a promiſe of being made General of the King's Army, when occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould require, and to that purpoſe received the Order of Knighthood.</p>
               <p>But fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> the King's Daughter, fixed her Eyes upon him, and from liking changed to Love, inſomuch that at length ſhe paſſionately doated on him; nor did ſhe refrain to let her Father know it, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed not to reſtrain her in her Inclination, but rather further it, in conſideration <hi>Bevis</hi> would renounce his Religion and become a Proſelyte
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59120:9"/> to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and undertook on a day to diſcourſe him on this occaſion. For taking him by the hand and leading him into a pleaſant Garden, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhade of Orange Trees, he made him ſit down by him, there being none but theſe two, all others being ſtrictly forbidden entrance, he thus began.</p>
               <p>Bevis, ſaid he, <hi>What if the moſt beautifull Lady of my Kingdom courted, honoured and adored by Kings and Potentates, ſhould not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding neglect their Favours, and caſt her Love upon one of a much lower degree, ought he not to condeſcend to any thing that ſhall be deſired for ſuch a Wife, and perhaps in a ſhort time a Kingdom into the Bargain?</hi> To this <hi>Bevis,</hi> when he had pauſed and bluſhed a while, making an humble obeiſance, replyed, <hi>That certainly that Man was moſt happy of all others, and ought to eſteem his Life and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes to mean a return for ſuch a gracious condeſcention. Ay,</hi> but continued the King, <hi>ſuppoſe that the caſe require him to abjure his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that your ſelf was the Man on whom this great Fortune would beſtow her ſelf, and could do it upon no other Terms, would you receive her upon this condition?</hi> Now whilſt the King was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiently expecting his Anſwer, <hi>Bevis</hi> fell upon his knees, and with hands and eyes up-lifted to Heaven, implor'd God to ſtrengthen his Faith, and protect him from falling into ſo great a Wickedneſs: Then riſing and bowing low to the King he ſaid, <hi>Moſt gracious Lord, if I muſt anſwer in this point, I could for the Lady you mention, who, if I may preſume to gueſs at your meaning, is no leſs than the fair Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, willingly Sacrifice all the Service of my Life, wade through Seas of Blood and Danger, nor think any thing ſufficient to merit ſo much condeſcending Goodneſs, no not my Life; but for the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that dearer part of Life, on which depends my eternal happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to renounce that, and deny the Lord that bought me: pardon Mighty Sir, if in this I muſt refuſe any complyance, no, not for ten Thouſand Worlds, nor all the Beauties of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King hearing <hi>Bevis</hi> thus unalterably fixed, and firm to the Faith he profeſſed, waved to preſs it further, and fell into other diſcourſe, and in the end, his great Affairs requiring him in the Palace, he departed. Nor was it long after, that <hi>Bevis</hi> ſhewed by proof how far he durſt haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard himſelf in the vindication of the Religion he profeſſed; for being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad on a <hi>Chriſtmas</hi>-day, well mounted and armed, he met ſixty <hi>Sarazens</hi> who as Enemies to our Saviour, began to joke upon <hi>Bevis</hi> in relation to the day, who returning them ſmart anſwers, which they took for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59120:9"/> their Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> they began to urge him more: to which he replyed, if he was but ſo well armed as Sir <hi>Guy</hi> his Father had ſometimes been in that Countrey, they ſhould ſoon perceive their vile <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſhould not be able to deliver them from his juſt anger. At that, ſaid one to the other, <hi>Do you hear how this Chriſtian Hound reviles our Prophet, and boaſts againſt us, wherefore let us no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger delay to chaſtize him with death.</hi> Vpon this, they all prepared to aſſault him, who with his Fiſt beating one of them (with his Neck broke) to the ground, wreſted from him his Sword, and ſo layed about him that heads and arms ſtrewed all the place, and in a ſhort time he drove thoſe that ſurvived before him to a River, wherein they deſperately threw themſelves, for fear of the Sword, and all but two periſhed, who haſted to the Court with the diſmal News, deſiring he might be put to death for curſing, as they ſuggeſted, their Prophet, the Law of the Land making it Death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King though he loved <hi>Bevis,</hi> yet inraged that the valour of his Kingdom was ſo much eclipſed by a Stranger, conſented, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that according to the Law of the Country, he ſhould ſuffer Death: of which fair <hi>Joſian</hi> having notice, haſtily entered her Father's Chamber and throwing her ſelf at his Feet, with Tears beſought him not raſhly to put his ſevere Commands in execution, but rather allow ſo much reſpite as the Parties might appear Face to Face, and then if it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Bevis</hi> was guilty of what had been witneſſed againſt him, he might more juſtly ſuffer him to receive his Doom. Theſe words of the beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Princeſs ſo far prevail'd that the King conſented, and thereupon ſhe diſpatched two Meſſengers to order <hi>Bevis</hi> to come and confer with her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his ſafety, who accordingly found him on his Couch, for he had ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained in the Battle above twenty Wounds, and was faint through loſs of Blood, yet ſeeing them approach, and ſuppoſing they were the two <hi>Sarazens</hi> that had eſcaped his Fury, and came now privately to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſinate him, in revenge of the death of their Fellows, he lookt ſo ſtern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on them, and began withall to gather his Sword that they retired from him, and durſt onely deliver their Meſſage at a diſtance: but he not crediting it, but rather ſuppoſing it a trick to decoy him into ſome ambuſh they had layed for his Life, as not knowing what the King had determined, he refuſed to go, threatning them with Death if they did not inſtantly depart: who carrying this Meſſage, or rather refuſal to the Princeſs, and ſhe knowing it was no time to dally when the Life of a Man whom ſhe loved above all Mankind was in the Ballance, laying
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59120:10"/> aſide all ſcruples and niceties, ſhe went attended with two Knights to his Chamber, where <hi>Bevis</hi> perceiving ſo bright a Creature, who had long ſince conquered his affections, roſe and threw himſelf at her Feet, expreſſing himſelf altogether unworthy of ſo great a favour, and expreſſed a thouſand thanks, with all imaginable reſpect, but ſhe not ſuffering him long to kneel, claſped her ſnowy Arms about him, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him gently from the ground, and as ſhe raiſed him ſtole a gentle kiſs, at which <hi>Bevis</hi> in a manner raviſhed with joy, began to demand the cauſe of her coming, who thereupon told him what had been witneſſed againſt him, and in what danger he was, and how ſhe had interceeded on his behalf, and obtained ſo much favour of the King, as to hear him in Perſon as to the matter whereof he ſtood accuſed, giving him Inſtructions how he ſhould behave himſelf, and promiſing to deal further with the King on his behalf, ſhe left the Knights to dreſs his Wounds and departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> won the favour of the Princeſs <hi rend="blackletterType">Ioſian,</hi> and kill'd a monſtrous Boar in the Forreſt, and fought with and overcome fifteen Forreſters, that eſtayed to take the head of the Boar from him. and how King <hi rend="blackletterType">Bradamound</hi> of <hi rend="blackletterType">Damaſcus</hi> proclaimed War, for <hi rend="blackletterType">Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and was overcome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEvis</hi> by this viſit of the fair Princeſs, having in a manner new Life put into him, his Wounds were ſoon cured, and his kind Advocate in the mean while had ſo taken off the edge of the Kings Anger, that when the matter was rightly underſtood, he was not only cleared but his Accuſers doomed, at their choice, either to ſight him, or to ſuffer Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; who having too lately experienced his more than humane force, gladly choſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atter. And now <hi>Bevis</hi> not only frequently enjoyed the preſence of the fair Princeſs, but gained great Reputation in the Court, being either loved or feared of all: And whilſt he was thus happy, News came by many of the Villagers who had ſled from their Habitations, That a monſtrous Boar was lately come into the Neighbouring Plains and had killed divers Shepherds and Travellers, ſo that the Forreſt was rendered impaſſible; and many aſſembling to deſtroy him, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59120:10"/> his fiery Eyes, his huge Tus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and his horrid Briſtles that ſtood up like a grove of Spears, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d from him, yet ſome of them were taken and carſhed to pieces, ſo that the entrance of the Den where he uſually aboad, was ſtrewed with the bones of the ſlain.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bevis</hi> waiting upon the Princeſs, at the arrival of this News, greatly rejoyced, as now finding an opportunity to ſignalize his valour for her ſake; and therefore without delay beſought her that he might enterprize the killing of this Monſter; and although ſhe uſed many Arguments, to diſſwade him from ſo great a danger, he nevertheleſs thirſting after Glory, ſo importuned her that ſhe conſented he ſhould try his fortune for ridding the Country of ſo great a miſchief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bevis</hi> having obtained leave, being well Mounted &amp; Armed, rode ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Forreſt, whilſt the Princeſs ſent after him her beſt Wiſhes, and having rouſed the Monſter, he came at him with open Mouth, his Briſtles ſtanding up an end, and with a horrible grunting or roaring ſet upon <hi>Bevis,</hi> who run againſt him with his Launce, but that ſhive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in pieces, and obliged him to draw his Sword, ſo that laying upon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59120:11"/> the Monſters Head, and nimbly avoiding the Fury of his Tusks, a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contention enſued, for ſo hard was the Skin of the Beaſt that he appeared, in a manner incapable of receiving any wound; inſomuch that he began to be weary with ſtriking, and a little retired; which the Boar perceiving, came at him more furious, and with his Tusk gave him a deep Wound in the Thigh; but as he attempted to redouble it, <hi>Bevis</hi> thruſt with great force, his Sword under his neather Iaw, where, the Skin being ſomewhat foft, it enter'd, and he following hard upon it, ſo far it went that it pierced the Boars heart, who thereupon fell down with a horrible groan, which made the Forreſt tremble, and breathed his laſt.</p>
               <p>The Boar thus dead, <hi>Bevis</hi> ſundred his Head from his Body, and bearing it upon his broken Launce, returned in Triumph with the ſpoil: but by the way being met by fifteen Forreſters, and they envying him the Glory of ſo great an Atchievement, reſolved amongſt themſelves to kill him, and take the head from him, that they might have the praiſe and reward as being taken for thoſe that ſlew the Boar; and ſo before he was well aware, they ſet upon him, incompaſſing him on every ſide; when about to draw his Sword, he found he had left it with the Body of the Boar, which made him throw down the Head, and with the Trun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheon of his Spear, beat two of them that attack'd him to the ground, ſorely bruiſed and wounded, and ſo laid about him, that in ſpire of the reſiſtance they made, he killed nine of them in a ſhore ſpace; and thoſe that remained, perceiving his matchleſs Proweſs, and the mighty force of his Stroaks, ſuppoſing him not to be of mortal Race, retired from him, and at length ſecured their Retreat, amongſt the Trees and Thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, and by that means ſaved their Lives, ſo that <hi>Bevis</hi> had now lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to take up the Boars head, and depart to the fair Princeſs, at whoſe feet he layed it; but ſhe, that he might gain the better eſteem with her Father, deſired him to carry it to the King, which he accordingly did, and was very kindly received, his Fame for this deed ſpreading far and wide, the Country People calling him their Deliverer; which did not a little pleaſe <hi>Joſian:</hi> ſo that, holding a private Conference with him, they paſſed their mutual Vows, never to Marry, by conſent, unleſs they Married each other.</p>
               <p>To croſs theſe happy Lovers, Fortune, that ſeldome long plays true, ſo ordered it that <hi>Bradamound</hi> King of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> having heard the Fame of <hi>Joſian</hi>'s Beauty, and earneſtly deſiring to have her to Wife, ſent boldly to demand her, of her Father King <hi>Ermine,</hi> ſwearing by his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59120:11"/> Gods if ſhe were not ſent, according to his deſire, he would come with an Army and take her by force, and not only ſo, but deſtroy his Country with Fire and Sword: at which inſulting Meſſage, King <hi>Ermine,</hi> being a little alarmed, and much inraged, aſſembled his Nobles in Council, to conſult what ought to be done on this occaſion, and at the inſtance of <hi>Joſian,</hi> who proteſted againſt <hi>Bradamound;</hi> it was agreed that the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſhould be returned, and <hi>Bevis,</hi> who gladly accepted it, made Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of King <hi>Ermine</hi>'s Forces; and for his great Credit amongſt the Souldiers, Dubbed him a Knight, from which time we muſt call him Sir <hi>Bevis;</hi> ſo that Forces being every where raiſed, an Army of 20000 Men were muſtered, and fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> the better to furniſh out her Knight, brought him a famous Steed called <hi>Arundel,</hi> almoſt as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned as <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> and having cauſed him compleatly to be armed, ſhe girded on a Sword called <hi>Morglay,</hi> the force of whoſe well temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed edge no Armour could reſiſt; and ſo claſping him in thoſe Walls of Steel, gave him a gentle Kiſs: at which he, ſmiling, ſaid, <hi>Dear Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, this Favour has made your Knight half a Conquerer before he enters on the War, and be aſſured no force can overcome the Man that undertakes your Quarrel.</hi> And now Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> being armed and mounted, cauſed the Trumpets to be ſounded and the Banners to be diſplayed, marſhalling his Men in ſuch orders as was admirable in ſo young a General, who had not been greatly acquainted with the Trains of War; ſo that now nothing but a Foe being wanting, the Army marched to meet the proud King <hi>Bradamound,</hi> before he entered the Country to ſpoil or waſte it; and accordingly Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> ſoon found him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped upon a large Plain, but the Pagan King being double the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſet little by it; yet after both Armies had for a while faced each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and bid defiance, a fearfull Combate enſued, ſo that the Showers of Arrows in a manner darkened the Sky, and what together with the claſhing of Swords, the Shouts of the Victors, the cryes of the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, the neighing of Horſes, and the noiſe of warlike Inſtruments, it ſeemed as if the diſſolution of all things was at hand, inſomuch that the wild Beaſts in the forreſts and mountains ſtood amazed and trembled, as wondring what ſo great a clamour and confuſion ſhould mean: and becauſe the <hi>Saraz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns</hi> much ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked about the Standart of their King to defend it, it being born by one <hi>Radiſon</hi> a Giant-like man, <hi>Bevis,</hi> the ſooner to diſcourage them, furiouſly with his Sword, broke into that quarter, and making his way over heaps of the Slain, diſperſing his Foes on e'ry ſide with a terrible deſtruction, he charged upon him with his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59120:12"/> Spear, which violently entering, his Shield pierced his Armour and run quite through his Body, ſo that he fell dead to the ground, and with a horrible g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oan, breathed out his laſt: And ſo proceeding to charge the reſt, he ſ on put them to the rout, and brought away the Standard, which ſo diſcouraged the Infidels, that they fell into confuſion, and fled into all Parts; when <hi>Bradamound,</hi> in a rage, ſuppoſing to reſtore the Battel, ranged through his diſordered People, and came where Sir <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> was cutting down whole Ranks, inſtantly reviling him by the name of Chriſtian Slave, and urging him to the Combate with many loud re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches; upon which a dreadfull Fight happened, the one ſighting through true courage, and the other through rage and diſpair; but at length Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> with a redoubled blow, cutting through <hi>Bradamound</hi>'s Helmet, which thereupon falling off, and he likewiſe to the Ground, cryed out for mercy, offering Cities, Towns and Caſtles for the Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of his Life, at which Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> ſmiling ſaid, is this the courage you ſhew for fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> to fetch whom, you have taken all theſe Pains, and cauſed ſo much bloodſhed, however, though you deſerve to dye for your bold preſumption, yet ſince I find you thus humble, make a ſolemn pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation that you will, whenever it ſhall be required, make a tributary Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalage and do Homage to King <hi>Ermine,</hi> holding your Kingdom at his Pleaſure, and I will not only ſave your Life, which is now in my Power, but ſet you free from the Swords of the inraged Souldiers, who thirſt after your Blood.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Bradamound</hi> being of a proud Temper, pauſed a while at theſe Conditions, impoſed upon him by the Conqueror, but finding he muſt conſent or looſe his Life, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th much regret he choſe the former, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly Proclamation was made, to ſpare the Lives of the flying Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, of whom already about 20000 were ſlain, inſomuch that the Plains bluſhed, and became ſlippery with Blood: and now the Battel being intirely won, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> giving the ſpoil to his Souldiers, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to King <hi>Ermine,</hi> to give him an account of his ſucceſs, who great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoyced thereat: but the Princeſs had a greater ſhare of the Ioy, to find her ſelf not only freed from the man ſhe hated, but in great likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to be Wedded to him ſhe moſt paſſionately loved; for now the King was ſo highly pleaſed with Sir <hi>Bevis</hi>'s brave and generous Conduct, that he recommended his Daughter to his private Entertainment and Reception, ſo that with his conſent he had have to viſit the beautifull Lady in her Chamber; who when they were together by themſelves, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beholding him, ſaid, with a ſigh, and then a roſie Bluſh over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59120:12"/> her Virgin Face: <hi>How long will it be, Sir Knight, before you will fully underſtand how much I love you, and how paſſionately? pardon my free expreſſion, I deſire to be your Wife:</hi> to which <hi>Bevis,</hi> over-raviſhed with Ioy, yet diſſembling, as well as he could, the exceſs of his Paſſion, replyed, <hi>Moſt lovely Maid, it cannot ſink into my Thoughts, that ſhe whom Kings have courted, and truly deſerves the greateſt Potentate on Earth, will condeſcend to wed a Stranger, who though perhaps nobly born, yet is deſtitute at preſent of thoſe mighty Fortunes, that your merit juſtly requires and abundantly deſerves: Thrones and Scepters I have none, nor can I incircle your head with a ſparkling Diadem, of which you may otherwiſe furniſh your ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> expreſſing himſelf as aforeſaid, and being miſconſtrued by the fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> ſhe ſaid he ſlighted and contemned her proffered Love, and therefore ſought thoſe excuſes, grew angry or appeared ſeemingly ſo, upbraiding him with too much neglect and coldneſs of affection, preſſing her reſentments ſo home, that ſhe urg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d he could not, as he ſaid, he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſcended and prove ſo cruel to one that dearly loved him, and ſo far proceeded on that Subject, that Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> ſenſibly ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing his honour touch'd, went diſcontented from her Chamber; nor did ſhe at that time further endeavour to ſlay him: However, ſoon after having notice that his diſcontent had creat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d an Indiſpoſition both of body and mind, ſhe ſhe ſent to comfort him, and in the end payed him a Viſit, again unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him the ſecrets of her Heart; and there it was concluded between them, that the Princeſs becoming a Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ian, he ſhould marry her: but knowing her Father would not ſuffer her to do it u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on that condition, it was further agreed, that with all her Iewels and Treaſure th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſhould ſecretly depart for <hi>England:</hi> but this Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>greement, being overheard by two of King <hi>Bradamound</hi>'s Knights, taken to the late Battle, they ſecretly adviſed King <hi>Ermine</hi> of it, and he thereupon conſulted them what was to be done to prevent a buſineſs t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y diſpleaſed him, for he would not by any means hear that his Dau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>r ſhould renounce the Religion of her Country, though otherways <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng enough ſhe ſhould be married to this renowned Stranger; ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he ſhould carry away the Lady by ſtealth, it was reſolved he ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured till matters could be better underſtood: but how with honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do it, the King was at a loſs, till in the end, theſe two evil Counſellors put it into his mind to ſend him with a Letter to King <hi>Bradamound</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho therein ſhould be required to make him his Priſoner. This bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g thought beſt to take the imputation of diſhonour from King <hi>Ermi</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59120:13"/> Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> was ſent for, and this Meſſage impoſed upon him, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that none was ſo worthy as himſelf to receive the Homage of a King he had brought into ſubjection: and then a Letter being provided for the purpoſe, ſealed with King <hi>Ermine</hi>'s Signet, contrary to the knowledge of fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> he undertook, upon the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> of his Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to perform the meſſage, adding that peradventure King <hi>Bradamound</hi> being now in his Strength, might refuſe what he in time of danger had promiſed, but if he might have his Horſe and Armour with him, he would force him, if ſo he refuſed, to tender his Homage, but being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded there-from by the King, as not convenient on this occaſion, he took his leave and departed towards <hi>Damaſcus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> having conquered King <hi rend="blackletterType">Bradamound</hi>'s Army, and brought him to do Homage to King <hi rend="blackletterType">Ermine,</hi> he and <hi rend="blackletterType">Ioſian</hi> plighted their troth. And how King <hi rend="blackletterType">Ermine</hi> purpoſely ſent him to <hi rend="blackletterType">Damaſcus</hi> to have him deſtroyed. How he threw down the Images there, and fought the whole City, but at laſt put into a Den of Dragons. What miſeries he ſuffered there, with other things.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure/>
               <p>At this news, the King cauſed all his Men to Arm, and as he was iſſuing over the Bridge, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> was come to the foot of it, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it was the King, made ſigns that he had a Meſſage to him, greeting him from King <hi>Ermine,</hi> who at the firſt ſight of him ſtarted back, as well knowing who it was; but being invironed with armed Men, and perceiving that Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> had ſheathed his Sword, he ſternly demanded his buſineſs, who, not forgetting his Diſtance, bending his knee to the Ground, delivered the Letter, the Contents of which were theſe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59120:14"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>To King <hi>Bradmound,</hi> King <hi>Ermine</hi> ſendeth Greeting:</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WHereas Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> of <hi>Southampton</hi> came lately a Stranger into my Court, and occaſioned the Quarrel between you and me, in diſſwading my Daughter to yield her ſelf your Wife, and has ſince gone about to make her renounce her Religion, intending privately to carry her away to his own Country, I thought good to advertize you thereof; wherefore, that there may be a right underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, for the future, I not thinking it convenient to lay hands on him my ſelf, have ſent him to you to chaſtize him at your Diſcretion; wherefore by no means let him ſcape, for he being once removed I doubt not, but it will be eaſie to work my Daughter to a complyance with your Demands, that all animoſities may ceaſe between us: and ſo we bid you heartily farewell.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This pleaſed <hi>Bradmound,</hi> and made him change his Countenance into terrour, as knowing Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> was now abandoned by King <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and put into his power to revenge the miſchief he had done him, and began immediately to conſult what Death or Torture he ſhould be put to, ſome gave Counſel to Burn him to Aſhes, others to Flee him alive, others again to draw him through the City, and hang him upon Tenters; but at laſt they concluded to caſt him into a deep filthy Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, where two fierce Dragons were kept: and now Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> plainly perceiving that there was miſchief plotted againſt him, ſaid, <hi>Sir as I am a Knight, let me dye the Death of a Souldier, in the Field; the which if you grant me a Horſe and Armour, to dye valiantly fighting, it will more redound to your Glory, and the courage of the Knights that ſhall have the honour to ſlay me.</hi> But the King without any reply, not thinking it fit to truſt ſo dreadfull a Man with Arms, who already unarmed, in a manner as he was, had made his City tremble, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to be ſeized; whereat Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> graſping a Sword, for he had broke his own in the former Combate, ſtood upon his defence; and although they drew up the Bridge, and hemmed him in on every ſide, he killed fifty Knights before he could be taken: but then, weary with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual fighting, and his Sword breaking at the ſame time, he yielded to fatal neceſſity; and no ſooner had the Infidels got him in their power, but they bound him in ſtrong Chains, and carried him to the Dungeon, where by Cords they let him down a wonderfull depth: but long he had
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59120:15"/> not been there e'er the Dragons perceiving him, came out of the corners where they had made their Dens, with terrible Crys and Howlings, frighting even thoſe that heard them from above, whereat Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> finding himſelf in a great ſtrait, and ready to be devoured by thoſe Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, redoubling his force, he burſt his Chains in ſunder, and found as Fortune would have it, in the place where he lay, an old ruſty Sword, with which, after a cruel fight, in which he received many Wounds from their Teeth and Claws, he killed the Dragons, and freed himſelf from the preſent danger, but ſuddenly fell into worſe; for having nothing wherewith to ſubſiſt, unleſs the fleſh of the Monſters he had ſlain, which were rank Poyſon, he muſt inevitably periſh for hunger; yet Death was not ſo terrible to him, as the thoughts he ſhould diſappoint Sir <hi>Sabre,</hi> and put his Miſtriſs in great ſorrow, who yet knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Vndertaking, and therefore might conclude he had forſaken her and proved falſe to his Vows. But whilſt he was in this perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, his Keepers perceiving from above that he had deſtroyed the Dragons, advertized the King thereof, who, that he might prolong his Miſery, in that noiſom place, and make him, as it were, dye a living Death, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that every day he ſhould have a Bowl of Bran and Water let down by Rope, with which, and the fleſh of Rats and Mice, which he caught in the Dungeon, he ſubſiſted for the ſpace of ſeven years.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> killed his Keepers, and eſcaped from the Dungeon, where he had been ſeven years, and after that the Grooms, and furniſhed himſelf with Horſe and Armour. How he killed a Knight and a Gyant. Stole fair <hi rend="blackletterType">Joſian</hi> from King <hi rend="blackletterType">Iour,</hi> that had Married her, Conquered another Gyant, and two Lyons, and arrived at <hi rend="blackletterType">Colen:</hi> And what there befell him.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIR <hi>Bevis</hi> being thus dead, in the conceit of the World, and the Princeſs <hi>Joſian</hi> ignorant of what had befallen him, was given by her Father to underſtand that he had left the Court privately, and was gene for <hi>England,</hi> where he had married a Princeſs of great Renown, to whom he was formerly betrothed, and there lived upon his Poſſeſſions,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59120:15"/> with an intention never to return; aſſuring her, that a Merchant had lately brought him this News; upon the recital whereof, the Royal Virgin wept abundantly, accuſing him of Ingratitude and Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, reviling the whole Sex for his ſake, and vowing to live a Virgin, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> returned, and ſhe found what had been related of him falſe: however, her Father preſſing her in this penſive and melancholly mood to comply with King <hi>Bradmound</hi>'s requeſt, and become his Queen; and finding her altogether averſe to him, he pitched upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, recommending him to her choice, <hi>viz. Jour</hi> King of <hi>Mambrat,</hi> a powerfull and wealthy Prince in thoſe parts, and by threats and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, obliged her to joyn her hands with his, though not her Heart; for although many Emperors, Kings and Potentates were at the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which was celebrated with exceeding Ioy and Pomp, ſhe alone was found Sorrowfull, often retiring and weeping bitterly for the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> by which ſhe injured her fair Eyes, and much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired her Beauty; and her Bedding, which is held the cuſtome of thoſe Countries, being deferred for a month, ſhe, in that time, procured of the wiſe Magicians of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> then at her Father's Court, ſuch Spells and Inchantments, that being worn, they, by ſecret power and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, took away all deſire in the King her Husband to bereave her of her Virginity; as ſhall be further mentioned hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bevis</hi>'s Horſe, Sword and Armour being in the poſſeſſion of King <hi>Ermine,</hi> he beſtowed them upon his new Son-in-law, but <hi>Arundel,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt mounting of King <hi>Jour,</hi> perceiving it was not his true Maſter, taking a Career over Hedges, Ditches and Places of the like danger, threw him with ſuch force, that the fall, by the mighty bruiſe, much indammaged his Life; which ſo vexed the King, that he cauſed him to be ſent to his Caſtle and kept in Chains till he was ſtarved to Death; but fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> for the ſake of his Maſter, daily fed him with her own hands, unknown to the King; and now began to miſtruſt, that there was ſome Treachery in the Caſe, foraſmuch as ſhe could not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> would leave a Sword, Armour and Horſe, he ſo intirely delighted in, when he might with the ſame caſe, as himſelf departed, have taken them with him: in which doubt we leave her a while, and return to Sir <hi>Bevis.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> having thus eſcaped his Foes, began now to faint, through hunger; and thereupon eſpying a Caſtle before him, and a beautifull La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, leaning over the Wall, he made up to it, and acquainted her with his neceſſities, intreating her to ſupply him, with ſuch Proviſion as ſhe had, telling her he was a Chriſtian Knight, who was upon the ſearch of Adventures, and that if it ſay in his Power, he would require her kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but ſhe hearing he was a Chriſtian, commanded him immediately to be gone, ſaying, That her Husband was a bloody Pagan Giant, and that if he knew he was there, he would ſuddenly come out and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him, as he bone many; but this nothing daunted Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> who rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed he had rather dye in Battle than through hunger, and therefore he was reſolved to Dine there that day: ſcarce had he ended theſe words but out came the Gyant, and ſtairing on him with a grim viſſage, ſaid, <hi>What art thou Fellow? and where cameſt thou by that Horſe, which if I miſtake not, is my Brother</hi> Grandure<hi>'s, whom thou haſt ſtole? bu however, I ſhall chaſtize thee for thus ſawcily approaching my Caſtle:</hi> and thereupon, e'er Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> could well reply, and give him an account, how he had gotten the Horſe, he came at him with a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and weighty Battle Ax, but miſſing him, he ſtruck his Horſe with ſuch force that he f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lled him to the Ground; but Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> leaping nimb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly off, cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with ſuch Fury, that he made the Giant give Ground; what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iring at a diſtance took his Bow that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng at the Wall, and ſhot at him with a forked Arrow, which entered his ſhoulder and greatly pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, yet thereat being more inraged, he followed him up ſo cloſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59120:17"/> that with a forcible blow, between the Giants neck and ſhoulders, where his Helmet was open, he ſtruck off his head, and his body thereupon falling to the ground made it tremble; at this the Lady ſcreeched out, and would have fled to the Woods; but Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> promiſing to do her no harm, ſhe was at laſt contented to ſtay, and ſet before him ſuch provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as the Caſtle afforded; and then ſetting free ſuch Priſoners as he fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd there, he departed to take a view of the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> where at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he was kindly received by the Patriarch, and there he made a vow for the ſake of fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> never to marry any but a ſpotleſs Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin; and now conſidering it was too late for him to go for <hi>England,</hi> to be Sir <hi>Sabres</hi> Champion: and of which enterpriſe he had been defeated by the treachery of King <hi>Ermine,</hi> he reſolved to go diſguiſed into <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> to know the cauſe why the King, who had ſo much deſerved of him, had ſo perfidiouſly dealt with him? but the rather to know what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the ſair Princeſs? the diſappointing of whom more ſenſibly grieved him, than all his other ſufferings: and whilſt he was muſing on this matter, a Knight overtook him, who had been of his former ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and related to him all that had paſſed on theſe occaſions, further informing him, that Queen <hi>Joſian</hi> though ſhe was married a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her will, ſtill kept him in remembrance, giving alms for his ſake to a great number of Palmers, and enquiring of every one what was become of him. This did not a little revive the ſpirits of Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> and put him upon a more earneſt enquiry, eſpecially where he might have a ſight of his fair Miſtris, and being informed ſhe kept her Court in the Caſtle of <hi>Mambrat,</hi> he haſted thither.</p>
               <p>Being arrived in the City and hearing the Queen gave alms to Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, he put himſelf in ſuch a weed, and leaving his horſe and armour in his Inn, haſted to the Caſtle gate, and there amongſt the reſt paſſed for a Palmer; but long he had not ſtaid there, before the Queen came with her Alms, the King and his Train being then gone a hunting, and when ſhe had diſtributed her bounty, and gently enquired of every one, whether they had lately ſeen or heard of Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> but not meeting with any ſuch news as ſhe wiſhed, ſhe retired to her Cloſſet, and in this manner bemoaned her ſelf: Alas ſaid ſhe, for the good Knight Sir <hi>Bevis</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he is gone and I ſhall never ſee him more; how could ſo brave a Knight be ſo much cruel, and unkind to a Virgin, that ſo highly eſteemed and adore him; ſure the beſt of men could never be guilty of the worſt of crimes; it muſt ſurely then, be that ſome who envied our peace and happyneſs has conſpired by treaſon to ſeparate
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59120:18"/> us, though it cannot be in their power to extinguiſh my love towards him; for a Queen as I am, I would willingly be diſrobed of my Royalty, to wander with that gallant Youth through Deſarts or Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes, and think nothing too much to endure or ſuffer for his ſake, whom I ſo dearly love; But O hard fortune, I ſhall never ſee him more! This ſaid, ſhe burſt forth into a flood of tears; which Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> who had all this while hearkned under the window noting, could not but let fall ſome tears to bear hers company, and finding an opportunity to ſpeak to <hi>Boniface</hi> her Page, he deſired him to acquaint the Queen, that he had a ſecret to impart to her, that highly concern'd her welfare; which being accordingly done, ſhe ordered he ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her coming down, in the retiring room, expecting from this Palmer, as moſt people uſually do what they earneſtly wiſh, ſome news of Sir <hi>Bevis.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure/>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> fought with, and killed a dreadful Dragon at <hi rend="blackletterType">Colen,</hi> obtained forces of the Biſhop his Uncle, ſailed for <hi rend="blackletterType">England</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his heritage, and by a wile got Armour and Horſes of Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Murdure,</hi> then taking part with Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Sabre,</hi> he ſent the other defiance, &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIR <hi>Bevis</hi> being come to <hi>Colen,</hi> and the fame of his valiant deeds and glorious atchievements, having reached that place before, he was highly welcomed, and the people were overjoyed, for now they hoped by his proweſs, to be delivered from the plague of their Country, which had deſtroyed ſo many of them, and layd many places waſt, <hi>viz.</hi> a dreadful Dragon, who kept a Cave not far from the City, and that night had poiſoned a Knight, whom many of the Inhabitants held invincible, and not to be conquered by mortal might; however at the cryes and intreaties of the Inhabitants, contrary to the knowledge of the Queen, who would not have ſuffered him to have undertaken ſo dangerous an enterpriſe, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and <hi>Aſcapart</hi> went early in the morning to ſeek the Monſter, and ſcarcely had they approached his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59120:20"/> Cave, when putting out his head he gave ſuch an horrible yell, that <hi>Aſcapart</hi> veryly ſuppoſing it to be the Devil, would advance no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereat Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> began to ſmile, ſaying, I thought you had not feared a whole Army, and are afraid of a Monſter? come take courage and you ſhall only be a looker on, whilſt I finiſh the work; and by this time the hideous Monſter being gotten out of his Cave, greedy of prey came at Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> lifting up his creſt and caſting fire and poyſon out of his mouth, his eyes burning like two Beacons, horribly hiſſing with a triple ſting, and a tail of infinite length, againſt whom the Knight ran forcibly with his ſpear, but his ſeales being harder than Braſs, it burſt in pieces and ſhivered in the Air; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he drew his truſty Sword, and laid at him furiouſly, but could by no means wound him, when the Dragon with his tail giving him a ſtroak, beat him from his Horſe, and very much bruiſed him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving likewiſe with his tallants rent his Armour; but Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dounted, avoiding as nimbly as he might, the ſtroak and ſtriking as he ſaw occaſion; but in the end the Dragon caſting poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon on him, and infecting the Air with his venemous breath, cauſed him a little to faint, and retireing towards a Well, he perceived the Monſter to make a ſtop ſome paces from it, and not to advance fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which gave him a breathing time; ſo that plainly perceiving, there was extraordinary virtue in the well, by reaſon of a Saint-like Virgins waſhing in it, that kept off his infectious enemy, he proceeded to drink ſome of the water, which he had no ſooner done, but he found his vigour renewed, and his ſtrength as at firſt, ſo that as often as he found himſelf annoyed with the poyſon, he retired thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as to a ſanctuary, and being refreſhed went again to the Combat; ſo that the Dragon being much bruiſed, and perceiving he could not overcome the Knight, began to take wing, where eſpying a bare place, not covered with ſcales or defence, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> reſolutly ſtept in and ſheathed his ſword in his ſide, following the thruſt ſo forcible that it peirced his heart, when with a horrible roar, as if a whole army of men had groaned out their laſt, he fell dead at his feet; of which victory Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> being exceeding glad, raiſed the ſcales of his neck, and cutting off his head, bore it into the City as in triumph, being met without the wall by old and young, with ſongs and muſick, ſtiling him their Deliverer, cauſing Bells to ring, and Bonfires to be made, and as a perpetual memory of this Victory, placed the Head upon the higheſt Tower in the City. Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> growing more
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59120:20"/> and more in eſteem with the Citizens of <hi>Colen,</hi> and knowing that the Biſhop of that City was his Fathers Brother, he reſolved to ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite him for Aid againſt Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> who kept his heritage, of the Earldom of <hi>Southampton</hi> from him, and taking his opportunity, when they were private together, he ſaid, Sir, you know my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, your Brother was unjuſtly ſlain by the connivance of my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and now the murtherer detains my Heritage; wherefore give Counſel, whether I ſhall atempt by force of Arms the regaining of it or deſiſt, and by your wisdom am I content be ruled, although I know Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> my other Vncle is already contending for it. 'Tis true replyed the Biſhop, and every year on a certain day they wage a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Battle, wherein one or other of their party is ſlain: wherefore it is my opinion, that you ought to contend for it your ſelf, as being the true Heir to the Earl your Father, and to further you in this matter, I promiſe to aid you with an hundred men at my own charge.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> glad of the profer made him by the Biſhop, went to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59120:21"/> 
                  <hi>Joſian,</hi> and acquainted her with this new undertaking, laying before her the neceſſity of it, and withal told her he would leave her in that City ſufficiently provided for, till the danger was over, and then fetch her in pomp, to poſſeſs their rightful heritage, and although ſhe was unwilling to leave his company, and could not part without tears, yet ſeeing it muſt be ſo ſhe conſented, and ſo with a kind kiſs for a time they bid a due to each other; for the men being ſhipped Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> went aboard, and within a while ſailing came to an anchor, in a Port about two miles from <hi>Southampton,</hi> where Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> being deſtitute of Armour to furniſh his men, thought of a ſtratagem to obtain it in this manner: <hi>viz.</hi> he ſent a Knight to the Caſtle of Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> to inform him, that underſtanding there was a great difference between him and another Knight named Sir <hi>Sabre,</hi> and that a Battle was ſhortly to be fought between them, an <hi>Almain</hi> Captain with a Band of reſolute Souldiers, was come to offer his ſervice, provided he would furniſh his men with Arms and Armour, that they might appear according to their quality, or elſe being Souldiers of Fortune, they were reſolved to make the like offer to his Enemy, by whom they doubted not but to be entertained.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> kindly accepted this profer, upon the condition propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and intreated them to land, which accordingly they did, and Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> with his men were highly treated, both by Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> and the Counteſs Sir <hi>Bevis</hi>'s Mother, who knew him not, for he had changed his name to that of Sir <hi>Gerard,</hi> ordering his men to call him by no other; when as Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> thus began, Noble Stranger, it may be you are ignorant of the cauſe that occaſions this difference between me and Sir <hi>Sabre,</hi> a hardy Knight whoſe reſidence is now in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and this it is, ſo it happened, that Sir <hi>Guy</hi> being ſlain by misfortune in a neighbouring Forreſt, who was Earl of this Town, I married the Lady his Counteſs my preſent Wife, and ſhe having had one Son by the Earl named <hi>Bevis,</hi> who proving extravagant and expenſive when of age I bought his Heritage of him, and he having conſumed the mony he received for it, left the Land and has not ſince been heard of; notwithſtanding this Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> who is his Vncle, being of late grown rich and powerful lays claim to it, and with many inroads and fierce Encounters diſturbs and invades my poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and now I have informed you of the juſtneſs of my cauſe, I hope it will exault your Courages to defend my right.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> having heard the foregoing relation and knowing it to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59120:21"/> be fabulous, had much ado to contain himſelf, and refrain from killing the murtherer of his Father, and the injurer of his Honour, in his own Caſtle; but conſidering it would be more generous, to do it in the field, he check'd at this time his anger, to wait a nobler opportunity, and ſo diſſembling the matter, he renewed his requeſt for Armour, Horſes, and Shipping, proteſting, if he might have them, to ſail im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and there put an end to the contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by making Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> his Priſoner, and bringing him bound to his preſence. At this Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> was well pleaſed, and ordered all things to be provided according as had been deſired, haſtening them to the enterpriſe, who being accordingly furniſhed with what they deſired, ſet ſail and landed in the Iſland, at what time Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> being near the Shoar, and perceiving Ships putting men on land, ſuppoſed them Enemies, and thereupon ſent for his forces to oppoſe them; but being convinced of the contrary, upon Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> cauſing his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Banner to be diſplayed, well known to him, and by that being aſſured it was his Nephew, he haſted to welcom him, and with much joy lead him to his Caſtle, and there they made report to each other, of all that had befel them ſince they parted; and thereupon Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> calling a Knight to him, and no longer deſirous to to diſſemble who he was, or refrain laying claim to his Heritage, ſent him to Sir <hi>Murdure,</hi> to let him know how he had been miſtaken and impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that he immediately expected a ſurrender of the Earldom; and would notwithſtanding puniſh him for treacherouſly killing his Father: when the Meſſenger came with this meſſage, Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> was at dinner with divers Friends, making great merriment, as not doubting by the help of his ſuppoſed Friends, to be revenged on Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> his mortal Enemy; but upon the delivery of the meſſage, finding himſelf deceived in his expectation, he grew exceeding wrath, and drawing his Daggar, being on the other ſide of the Tabe, he threw it with great force at the Knight, but miſſing him, it ſtruck into the breaſt of his own Son, who was then waiting at the borad, whereupon he fell down dead, and the other fled, relating all that he had ſaid and ſeen, to Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> who gave him for this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice forty pounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:59120:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> and Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Murdure</hi> prepared for War. How <hi rend="blackletterType">Joſian</hi> had like to have been Raviſhed; and how ſhe was reſcued from the Flames, and brought together with the Gyant <hi rend="blackletterType">Aſcapart,</hi> to the Iſle of <hi rend="blackletterType">Weight:</hi> and what other matters happened.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIR <hi>Bevis,</hi> as we ſaid, being in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> we muſt there leave him a while, and return to <hi>Joſian</hi> whom we left at <hi>Colen,</hi> and with her the Giant <hi>Aſcapart</hi> as her Guard, to prevent any danger that might befall her. So it fell out, That <hi>Joſian</hi> had not been long here, after the departure of Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> but Sir <hi>Miles</hi> an Earl of that Country, caſting his Eyes upon her admirable Beauty, fell deſperately in love with her, and began in a paſſionate manner, to court her to his pleaſure, but ſhe refuſing his proffer'd Love with disdain, he reſolved if he could not have his Will of her fairly, to have it by force, and in a manner told her his intent, to which ſhe replied, Sir, although Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> is abſent, yet have I here with me <hi>Aſcapart,</hi> that will not ſee me wronged: and by this means, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving underſtood in whom ſhe repoſed her confidence, reſolved to get him out of the way, whilſt he acted his wicked purpoſe, and ſo feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Letter to him, in Sir <hi>Bevis</hi>'s name, how that he muſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately come to him, to the Caſtle in the Sea, ſtanding a league from the Shoar; the unthinking Giant went, when he no ſooner entred the Caſtle, but it was ſhut upon him, by thoſe that carried him, and the boat, as Sir <hi>Miles</hi> had agreed with the Boatmen, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately rowed back again; and then he made his freſh attempts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> telling her what he had done with <hi>Aſcapart,</hi> and now ſhe had nothing to hope in, but muſt yield to his pleaſure or dye; whereupon ſhe ſecretly ſent a truſty Meſſenger, to certifie Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhe was in, which required his ſpeedy aid: and then to delay the falſe Knight, ſhe told him, if he would marry her, he ſhould have his will of her, but if he otherways attempted it, ſhe would rather dye than ſuffer it to be done.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Miles,</hi> as I ſaid, being paſſionately in love with the fair Queen, ſtuck not at any thing ſhe propoſed, ſo that he might enjoy her, and having
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59120:22"/> told her he would aſuredly do it, and thereupon obtaining a kiſs, the day was appointed, to be the next, and thereupon he prepared all manner of ſumptuous Chear and Muſick, inviting many Barrons, Knights, and Ladies to his wedding, and ſo married they were early in the morning, and the day being ſpent in feaſting; when it grew night and Supper ended, fair <hi>Joſian</hi> was led to her Bride-Chamber, and ſoon after, impatient of delay, came Sir <hi>Miles</hi> with many atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, but ſhe intreated him for modeſties ſake to ſend away his Train, and ſhe would be his Chamberlain; ſo that at his command all departing, and they left together, ſhe finding now no other way to ſave her honour, made a ſlip-knot of her Girdle and caſting it over his Neck, ſtrangled him, and afterward hung him upon a beam. And his Barrons and Knights finding him not abroad in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as he was wont, imputing it to his new Love Incounters with the fair Bride, every one wiſhing himſelf in his place; ſome went to hunting, and others to the Church; but coming home at noon, and yet not finding him out of his Chamber, they had great marvel, inſomuch that one of them went to ſee what was the matter, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the door, ſaid, <hi>Ariſe Earl</hi> Miles, <hi>for you have ſlept a great while, wherefore I cannot but think your head akes, will you pleaſe to have a Candle? Nay,</hi> replyed Ioſian, <hi>I will undertake his Head ſhall ake no more, for I have unknit the wedding, and yonder you may ſee him hanging, my honour he ſhall never deſtroy, though for what I have acted, you may do with me as you pleaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The death of Sir <hi>Miles</hi> once known to his Friends, they made great ſorrow for it, and with much anger proceeded to burn the fair <hi>Joſian</hi> at a ſtake, ſo that the Fire being ſet in order, and kindled by the Sea ſide, <hi>Aſcapart,</hi> who beheld it from the Caſtle, imagining that Queen <hi>Joſian</hi> his Miſtris was in danger burſt in ſunder the Iron gates, and entring a Fiſhers boate, juſt come into the Port, he rowed himſelf to the place where the Fire was, and found it to be true, as he had dread, for there he beheld the Queen in her ſhift, ready to be put into the fire, and whilſt he was deviſing how to reſcue her, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> came riding up, and ſeeing <hi>Aſcapart,</hi> ſaid, Thief where has thou been? where has thou left <hi>Joſian</hi> my fair Queen, whom I gave thee in charge, that ſhe is thus forced to ſend for me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver her from danger? whereupon asking his pardon, he told him all that had happened, and ſhewed him in what danger the Queen ſtood, who had before their coming been ſacraficed in the Flames, had
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59120:23"/> not the Prieſt been long in ſhrieving her. This ſight ſo enraged Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> that bidding <hi>Aſcapart</hi> follow him, he broke through the throng, and with his Sword cut all in pieces before him, in ſo much that the people fled amazed, crying on every hand for mercy, whilſt <hi>Aſcapart</hi> on the other ſide, laid them on heaps with his Club, felling and braining whole ranks at a blow, and having made great ſlaugther and cleared the Coaſt, <hi>Joſian</hi> being left alone, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> cauſed her to cloath her ſelf, and mount behind him, and together with <hi>Aſcapart</hi> they took ſhipping, and ſailed to the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> where they were lovingly receeived by Sir <hi>Sabre,</hi> and his Knights. <hi>Joſian</hi> returning great thanks to Heaven for her deliverance, and there related to Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> all that had befell her, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> and Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Murdure</hi> muſtered their Armies, and of the mortal Battle fought between them, in which the latter was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, and taken Priſoner. How he was boiled alive, and how the Counteſs his Wife, broke her Neck: and how Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> took poſſeſſion of his Eſtate, &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIR <hi>Bevis</hi> and Sir <hi>Sabre,</hi> reſolving to purſue Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> to death, ſent their ſummons into all parts, to require their Friends to come to their Aid, ſending, the better to encourage them, gifts of Gold and Silver very liberally, ſo that many Earls, Barrons, and Knights came ſlocking to their Standard, with their Pages, and their Attendants, who according to their Degrees were liſted, and entred into the Service; of which Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> having notice, was exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fretted in his mind, and therefore conſulted with the Counteſs his Wife, what was beſt to be done for their ſafeties, who adviſed him to ſend to his Brother the Emperour, and ſhe would do the like to her Father the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> to let them know their diſtreſs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>require their ſpeedy Aid, which ſhe doubted not to obtain, with many more Knights of Renown, in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and then like a Tempeſt falling upon <hi>Bevis, Sabre</hi> and their Fellows, you may ſoon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59120:23"/> put them to the ſlight, wherefore, ſaid ſhe, in no manner let your Courage fall you.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Soon after the King was beaten down, he retired out of the battle to refreſh himſelf, and having put on freſh Armour, and remounted he came again with great fury to the Fight; ſo that great ſlaughter enſued, and Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> ſtill ranging through the Battle making horrible deſtruction whereever he came, advanced ſo far that he broke into the preſs where Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> had ſlain and unhorſed many, ſaying Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59120:24"/> Let thoſe alone and turn thee hither, but Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> ſeeing it was Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> who had vowed his death, he uſed many endeavours to ſhun the fight; but Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> preſſing on, and thinking to give him a forcible blow, thereby to diſpatch him at once, he by ſwiftly turning his Horſe avoided it, yet the Sword falling on his Horſe, clove his crupper in ſunder, ſo that he fell down dead, but Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> was remounted by his Men, and a while made reſiſtance, but finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to weak for his adverſary, he retyred within the ranks of his Men, and left them to the fury of Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> who mounted on <hi>Arundel</hi> his Steed, laid about him on every ſide, with his truſty Sword <hi>Morglay,</hi> nor did his Horſe fail with his heels and teeth to fight couragiouſly, giving to many their mortal wounds; ſo that the Plain whereon they fought, blſhed with blood, and was covered with dead bodies, ſo that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Enemies was leſſened: and at the ſignal given <hi>Aſcapart</hi> advanced with his men on foot, for by reaſon of his monſterous ſize no Horſe could bear him, and with his huge Club overthrew whole Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, in ſo much that he drove a thouſand men before him, like a flock of Sheep to the Sea-ſide, who fearing a worſer death, leaped into the waves, and were moſt of them drowned; but a very few getting to the Ships, that lay at Anchor in the Road; and then returning where his Men fought, he broke through the main Battle of <hi>Scots,</hi> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried all before him, making lanes whereever he came, till he arrived where Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> was fighting, and had done wonders.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> no ſooner beheld <hi>Aſcapart,</hi> but calling him to him, ſaid, Mark well the perſon that fights on younder Steed, and be ſure you let him not eſcape our hands, for that is Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> the cauſer of all this miſchief; whereupon <hi>Aſcapart</hi> in all haſte made thitherward, and when Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> would have fled from him, he caught him in his Arms, Horſe and Man, and bore him, in ſpite of the reſiſtance that was made, into the Caſtle; and now Sir <hi>Morris</hi> being ſlain by Sir <hi>Sabre,</hi> and the King of <hi>Scots</hi> being no longer able to maintain the Battle, the Souldiers fled on all parts; which the King perceiving and not being able to reſtraine the Flight fled likewſe, and getting into a Ship, prepared for that purpoſe, he ſailed away Weſtward to a ſtronge Caſtle of his in the Sea. And now Sir <hi>Murdure</hi> being in the Caſtle, he was condemned to be put into a Cauldron of ſcalding Pitch and Brimſtone, where he miſerably periſhed; and this he had as a puniſhment for the murther of Sir <hi>Guy</hi> Father to Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and Earl of <hi>Southampton;</hi> of which the Counteſs his Wife being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59120:25"/> ſhe leaped in a deſperate mood, from the Battlements of her Caſtle, and broke her Neck.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> was married to Queen <hi rend="blackletterType">Ioſian,</hi> and the honours that were done him. His Horſe having killed King <hi rend="blackletterType">Edgars</hi> Son, he abjured the Land to ſave him, and went to ſeek adventures in ſtrange Countries; and what befel him on this occaſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure/>
               <p>BEing thus rid of of his mortal Enemies, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles Companions, took leave of the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and ſailed to <hi>Southampton,</hi> where finding his Mother dead, by the means aforeſaid, he cauſed her notwithſtanding, to be honourably buryed; and ſo took
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59120:25"/> poſſeſſion of his Caſtle, and Heritage, and ſending for the Biſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> and many other noble Perſonages, he was by the ſaid Biſhop, married to his beloved Queen <hi>Joſian,</hi> and never was Queen ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be diſrobed of her Royalty, nor Knight ſo pleaſed with a Queen; and ſoon after going to <hi>London,</hi> to do homage to King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> for his Earldom, and having told him his name, and by what right he claymed that Heritage, the King made him Marſhal of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> delivering the ſtaff that his Father Sir <hi>Guy</hi> had before him: ſo that returning home he was highly eſteemed and honoured by King, Peers and Peſants ſpending his eſtate liberally and in giving Alms re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring from his 7 years impriſonment what it was to ſuffer hunger.</p>
               <p>Yet growing great in Offices and places of honourable truſt, he at laſt ſtirred up the envy of one Sir <hi>Brian</hi> of <hi>Cornwal</hi> againſt him, as having ſome of the Offices beſtowed upon him by the King; that were formerly his; ſo that about <hi>Whitſontide</hi> when ſundry Knights were courſing and raceing on their gallant Steeds, forty pounds in gold was propoſed for a three mile Courſe, on the Horſe that run beſt; when Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> being preſent and knowing none might compare to <hi>Arundel,</hi> he undertook in honour of the day to ride with the reſt, and although two Knights having unexpectedly the ſtart were got half a mile before, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> gave <hi>Arundel</hi> the reins, who flew forth like the wind, and immediately overtook them, and paſſing by, was at the Races end before they could imagine he was gotten two miles, which made the Kings Son ſo much in love with the Horſe for his goodneſs, and for whoſe ſake, as the ſtory ſays, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> built the Caſtle of <hi>Arundel,</hi> calling it after his Horſes name, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired at any rate to have him, but Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> required of him to ask any thing elſe and he ſhould freely have it, yet as for his Horſe no Gold, nor Caſtles, nor Towns, nor Favour could aſſure him to part with him, upon which the Prince w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tching his opportunity, reſolved to take him by force out of the ſtable, but as he attempted to do it, <hi>Arundel</hi> knowing it was not his Maſter, lifted up his Heels, and gave him ſuch a blow on the Head that his brains ſlew out.</p>
               <p>When King <hi>Edgard</hi> heard his own Son was ſlain, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how, he was exceeding wrath, and aſſembling his Councel, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to them, that ſince Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> his denying his Horſe to his Son, had made him attempt what occaſioned his death, it was ſit that he ſhould dye for it a cruel death, urging that he might be drawn to pieces with wild Horſes; but his Councel declared they could paſs
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59120:26"/> no ſuch ſentence upon him, ſeeing he no hand in the death of the Prince. But Sir <hi>Brian</hi> of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> reſolving to do him a diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſtarting up, ſaid, <hi>Though they could not indeed meddle with Sir</hi> Bevis <hi>for this matter, yet the Horſe ought to be ſlain;</hi> which was agreed on all hands: whereupon Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> humbly beſought the King, that rather than he ſhould looſe his Horſe, he would permit him to abjure the Land, which being granted, he ſurrendred up his Offices and places of Honour, which was that which Sir <hi>Brian</hi> aimed at, and made over his Lordſhips and Heritage to his Vncle Sir <hi>Sabre;</hi> and ſo with <hi>Joſian</hi> Sir <hi>Terre</hi> and <hi>Aſcapart,</hi> he took his leave of <hi>England,</hi> and from this time <hi>Aſcapart</hi> ploted how he might bring it about to ſeize <hi>Joſian,</hi> and carry her back to King <hi>Jour,</hi> of which more hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi rend="blackletterType">Ioſian</hi> was brought to bed of two Children in a Forreſt, and was carried away by a Gyant. How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> diſpoſed of the Children. How he juſted, and won a fair Lady for Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Terre;</hi> and how Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Sabre</hi> recovered <hi rend="blackletterType">Ioſian</hi> and killed the Giant.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIR <hi>Bevis</hi> and his Company, being now again in a ſtrange Land, and <hi>Joſian</hi> by this time great with Child, as they rid through a Forreſt, ſhe fell in travel, ſo that alighting they cut down boughs with their ſwords, and made her a Bower for her conveniency, paving it with Ruſhes and ſoft Leaves, and offered their aſſiſtance to help her in that extreamity, but ſhe through modeſty excuſing it, deſired them to retire, and leave her to the protection of Heaven; ſo that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Aſcapart</hi> as a ſentinel at a diſtance, to watch that no rude per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or wild beaſt might approach, to annoy or diſturb her, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and Sir <hi>Terry</hi> went to ſeek for ſomewhat for her refreſhment; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which ſpace <hi>Aſcapart,</hi> when ſhe was delivered of two Sons, took her on his Back in the woful condition ſhe was in, in vain crying for help, her Lord being out of hearing, and haſted through Woods and Forreſts over Hills, Rocks and Mountains towards <hi>Mambrat,</hi> there to deliver her to King <hi>Jour</hi> her former Husband in hopes of a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59120:26"/> great reward and honour; ſo that when Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and Sir <hi>Terrey</hi> returned, they found only the Children in the Bower, and perceiving <hi>Aſcapart</hi> gone, they eaſily gueſſed at what had befallen, and made great ſorrow for this loſs, but finding it no boot to ſtay there Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> wrapped up the Children in a rich mantle their Mother had left behind her, and paſſing on met a man, of whom they inquirid, if he ſaw not a Giant carrying a Lady that way, who anſwered he did not; then ſaid Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> what is your buſineſs? he replied, I am a Forreſter, then will you, ſaid he, take home with you this Child, and cauſe it to be chriſtened by the name <hi>Guy,</hi> and here is ten marks in hand, and when you have kept it ſeaven years, inquire for one <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> and bring it to him, and you ſhall have ſtore of Gold for ſo doing: The man upon theſe conditions, having gladly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Infant, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and Sir <hi>Terry</hi> paſſed on, and meeting with a Fiſher-man, diſpoſed of the other in the ſame ſort, directing his name to be <hi>Miles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Long theſe Champions rid together, yet could they get no ſight nor tidings of <hi>Aſcapart,</hi> who went through Woods and By-ways to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent diſcovery, nor reſted they till they entred a fair Town, and there betook themſelves to an Inn to reſt; but long they had not been there, er'e looking out at the Window, they ſaw a gallant Train of Horſe-men, exceedinly well mounted on Horſes with rich Trappings, and Heralds on every ſide diſplaying their Arms and Banners, which made them enquire of their Hoſt, the occaſion of ſo great a concourſe, who told them that on the morrow there would be held a great Iuſting in that Town, for a fair Virgin, Daughter to the Duke, who being old and not expecting long to live, for the honour he bears to Arms, has ſet her the prize, and with her, all his Lands and Poſſeſſions after his death, of his valour who can win her, by carrying the day from the reſt of the Knights, Earls, Dukes and Barrons.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> being now at home, in poſſeſſion of great Fortunes, happened on a night to dream, that Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> was much diſtreſſed, through the means of <hi>Aſcapart</hi> the Giants treachery, and telling his dream to his Wife, ſhe adviſed him to go in ſearch of his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew; and thereupon taking twelve Knights with him in Palmers weeds, though under them they were well armed, he croſſed the Seas and having paſſed through many Lands, as he approached <hi>Mambra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> he eſpyed the Gyant haling fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> who cryed out pitiouſly to him and his Companions for help, as knowing that if ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to firſt her Husband, he would put her to death, and thereupon Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> and his Knights commanded him to let her go, but he ſternly refuſing it, they aſſailed him on all ſides; whereupon quitting her bound as ſhe was, and therefore incapable of flying away, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himſelf to his Club, and laid at the Knights with great fury, but they being nimble, ſtill avoided his blows, and in the end having tired him, Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> whilſt the others maintained the ſight, ſtepped in, and with his ſword run him through, ſo that he fell dead to the ground; where leaving him, he lead <hi>Joſian</hi> to the next Inn, and there with a certain oyntment, diſcoloured her fair face that ſhe might not be known, but having ſpent all their mony and proviſion, they went to require a ſupply, at a Caſtle where Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and Sir <hi>Terrey</hi> were lodged, when Sir <hi>Terrey</hi> coming to the gate knew his Father and lead him in with great joy, nor was Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> a little glad when he heard <hi>Joſian</hi> was recovered; whereupon Sir <hi>Terrey</hi> proceeded as it had been agreed, to wed the fair <hi>Elinor,</hi> which was done with great feaſting, pomp, and ſplendor, and her Father ſoon after dying, he poſſeſſed himſelf of all the Eſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59120:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How King <hi rend="blackletterType">Iour,</hi> making war upon King <hi rend="blackletterType">Ermin,</hi> was defeated, and taken Priſoner by Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis.</hi> How he had the Kingdom of <hi rend="blackletterType">Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> delivered to his Son <hi rend="blackletterType">Guy,</hi> and again ſubdueing King <hi rend="blackletterType">Iour,</hi> took <hi rend="blackletterType">Mambrat,</hi> with other things of note.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>KING <hi>Jour,</hi> having a long time in vain expected his Wife, reſolved to greive for her no more, but to be revenged on her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thereupon made war on his Countries, of which Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> receiving inteelligence by a Palmer, gathered a great Company, and leaving Sir <hi>Terrey</hi> with his new Wife, took with him Sir <hi>Sabre,</hi> and his two Sons <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Miles,</hi> who were grown by this time to perfection, reſolving to aſſiſt his Father-in-Law, of whoſe coming King <hi>Ermine</hi> was exceeding glad, and humbly beged his pardon, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to make him amends, for the injury he had done him, to be Chriſtened with all his people, whereupon Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> ſent to <hi>England</hi> for Clergy-men, who inſtantly came and performed that good Office: Yet King <hi>Jour</hi> drawing near with twenty thouſand <hi>Sarazens,</hi> deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Countrey before him, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> being made General of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony,</hi> raiſed an Army likewiſe to meet him, and defying each other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a plain field, a dreadful battle began; whereupon Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and his Knights ſo laid about them, that they overthrew and cut in pieces whole Ranks of men, and grew at length ſo terrible, that where ever they came, the enemies fled before them, when coming to King <hi>Jour</hi> he beat him from his Horſe, and there had ſlain him, had not a Troop of freſh men inſtantly come in to his Reſcue, ſacrificing their lives to defend him, who no longer truſting to his forces, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day was loſt, betook himſelf to flight, and was followed by ſuch of his men, who eſcaped the ſword, yet Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> purſued ſo hard after him, upon his ſwift Horſe <hi>Arundle,</hi> that he overtook him, and made him his priſoner, having ſoon after for his Ranſome, twenty tuns of Gold, three hundred Bales of Silk, and as many white Steeds, with three hundred Cups of Gold and Silver, making him at the ſame time ever quit claim to the fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> and to be in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Amity with King <hi>Ermine.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:59120:28"/>
               <p>For this and other great ſervices, King <hi>Ermine</hi> offered to give him his Crown; and the Government of this Kingdom, but he refuſed it, yet accepted it for <hi>Guy</hi> his eldeſt Son, who was ſolemnly crowned King of <hi>Armony,</hi> and the old King not long after died; upon which King <hi>Jour</hi> fretted at his diſgrace, reſolved again to invade the Countrey, and thereupon thinking Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> did theſe wonders, through the ſtrength of his Horſe, he reſolved to get him by fraud, and ſent on <hi>Robion</hi> a cunning fellow to ſteal him out of the ſtable, who charming his keepers, as alſo the Horſe with ſpells and ſleeping drenches brought him away: But ſcarcely had he reached <hi>Mambrat</hi> with him, before Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> eſpied him, and leaping up behind him, felled him dead with the truncheon of a ſpear, but er'e he could<figure/> get away, the <hi>Sarrazens,</hi> that had beheld what was done, came running and aſſailed him on every part, and although he valiantly defended himſelf- they hardly put him to it, which <hi>Joſian</hi> having perceived from the Turret of a Caſtle, advertiſed Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> who
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59120:29"/> with other Knights haſted to his aid, and ſlew the <hi>Sarrazens</hi> in great number, ſo that happy was he, that could firſt recover the City. This made King <hi>Jour</hi> exceeding wrath, and immediately to ſend to his Brother <hi>Bradwin</hi> to come to his ſuccor, who was King of <hi>Surry,</hi> making at the ſame time great ſacrifices, offers and vows to <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> for his ſucceſs; and thereupon King <hi>Jour</hi> grown deſperate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to end the ſtrife, by ſingle Combate with Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing for that purpoſe towards <hi>Armony</hi> with three thouſand men, he deſied him, telling him that having ſlain his Men, bereaved him of his Wife, and done him other miſchiefs, he would now try it out with him to wreck his own revenge; and if it ſo fell out, that he ſlew him, he would poſſeſs himſelf of the Land of <hi>Armony;</hi> but if himſelf was ſlain, <hi>Mambrat</hi> ſhould be delivered to Sir <hi>Bevis:</hi> Theſe Conditions agreed on, and ſworn to on either part, they went into a little Iſland to fight the Combat, and there drawing their Swords, they furiouſly laid at each other, the one animated by diſpair, and the other by true valour; but after many wounds given and received, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> with a forcible blow, burſt King <hi>Jour</hi>'s Helmet in ſunder, cutting through his Shield, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as he held it up to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; ſo that he brought him to the ground both horſe and man: but the King nimbly got up again, and calling upon <hi>Mahomet</hi> for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor, began the fight anew, at which Sir <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>evis</hi> alighted to be upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual terms, and with another ſtroak felled him again; ſo that now he had him at his mercey, whoſe life he notwithſtanding ſpared, yet ſent him to a ſtrong Caſtle, and doomd him a priſoner for his life, when taking his Armour and Enſigns of Royalty, he went with a good Company of Souldiers to <hi>Mambrat,</hi> where the Citizens ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him to be their King, immediately opened their Gates; ſo that entring with his men, he ſoon made himſelf Maſter of it, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all that reſiſted to the ſword, and obliged the reſt to abjure their Mahumitiſme cauſing himſelf there to be crowned, by which Queen <hi>Joſian</hi> was twice Queen of <hi>Mambrat.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59120:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Sabrey</hi>'s Heritage being taken away, he came with Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> to recover it; and how the later maintained a great Battle in <hi rend="blackletterType">London,</hi> wherein he killed Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Brian</hi> of <hi rend="blackletterType">Cornwel,</hi> his mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and how he was reſtored to the Kings Favour, and Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Sabre</hi> to his Land.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIR <hi>Sabre</hi> being now with Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> as they rod forth a hawking on a day, news was brought him, that King <hi>Edgar</hi> had ſeized on his Inheritance by the advice of Sir <hi>Brian</hi> of <hi>Cornwal</hi> his Steward, and turned out his Wife and Children, of which he had no ſooner notice, but he asked Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> leave to depart for <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> but he would not ſuffer him to go alone, promiſing to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him, and his Son, with his Queen and his two Sons, and many courageous Knights, when landing at <hi>Southampton,</hi> he raiſed a great power of his Friends, and marched towards <hi>London,</hi> where the King was; then Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> leaving his Army at <hi>Putney,</hi> went with twenty Knights only to waite upon the King, and having ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance to his preſence, after Reverence done, deſired to know, Why Sir <hi>Sabre</hi>'s Eſtate had been ſeiſed? to whom the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, It was done at the inſtance of Sir <hi>Brian</hi> his Stward, but however he had ſince bethought himſelf, and would ſoon reſtore it; but Sir <hi>Brian</hi> being preſent, boldly ſtarted up and ſaid, it ought not to be done, ſaying moreover to Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> that he wondred how he durſt, being a baniſhed man, return, and that for his preſumption he ought to be hanged, or put to ſome other ſhameful death; to this Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> replyed neither good nor bad, but making his Reverence to the King, departed. But the revengeful Steward not ſo ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, knowing where he inn'd with his Knights, cauſed the City-Gates to be locked, and the Chains to be drawn croſs the ſtreets, and raiſed a Cry at midnight, that every one who could bear Arms, ſhould aſſault Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> in his Lodging, to revenge the death of the Kings Son ſlain by his Horſe <hi>Arundel,</hi> of which treachery Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> having notier, ordered his Squire to haſten his Sons to his aid with the Army, and thereupon mounting <hi>Arundel,</hi> he met Sir
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59120:30"/> 
                  <hi>Brian</hi> at the head of the people he had raiſed; and ſaid to him, come on now, you are an old Knight of War, and ſo they run upon each other, but Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> miſſing with his Spear, Sir <hi>Brian</hi> run him quite<figure/> through the Shield, and clove it in ſunder, which ſo much ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed him, that drawing his Sword <hi>Morglay,</hi> he ſmote him with a down right ſtroak, and clove his Honnet and head in ſunder, and charging upon his men made a great ſlaughter of them, inſomuch that the ſtreets ran with blood, and ſo paſſing on to <hi>Broad-ſtreet,</hi> he met di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Lumbards,</hi> that came to aſſail him, but ſoon ſcattered and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed them, whilſt his other Knights were not idle, but made a great ſlaughter and havock of the Multitude; yet finding themſelves hard beſer, they made towards <hi>Ludgate,</hi> to poſſeſs themſelves of it, but found it ſhut and gaurded, whereat Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> commanded them to open it, and let him out, who refuſing to do it, a great fight was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun anew, and ſo well Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> behaved himſelf that he brought ſix hundred men to the ground, without receiving a wound himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:59120:30"/>
               <p>The news of Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> his danger coming to the ear of his Wife and Sons, the former fell in a ſound, but the two later raiſed and revived her, telling her they would bring him ſpeedy aid, reſolving if they found him ſlain, to deſtroy and lay waſt the City, and ſo mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they led their Hoaſt by great marches, and not only found their Father alive, but manfully defending himſelf, yet exceeding weary with ſo great a toil and blood-ſhed, at what time more Citizens came to the aid of their Fellows under the leading of a ſtout Lumbard and ſtrong, who charged Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> with great fury, but ſped no better than Sir <hi>Brian</hi> of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> for with the firſt ſtroak Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> gave him he ſevered his head from his ſhoulders, and now Sir <hi>Sabre, Guy</hi> and <hi>Miles</hi> laying furiouſly about them, the Citizens fled in great diſorder, and ſhut themſelves up, as many as could, in their own Houſes and in Bulwarks then built to defend the Walls; and ſome fled to the King, who then kept his Court in the Tower, whereupon Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> had the intire-poſſeſſion of the City; yet would he not uſe any violence to thoſe that reſiſted him not, nor ſuffer his Sons, who in the hear of their youthful blood purpoſed, to ſeek and fire the City, but immediately cauſing a Retreat to be ſounded, he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew his Forces and retired to <hi>Southampton,</hi> where he took poſſeſſion of his Eſtate, ſending to the King to excuſe what had been done on his part with the manner how it fell out; ſo that the fault being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether laid upon Sir <hi>Brian,</hi> who was now dead, the King was no ways offended with Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> but confirmed him and Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> in their Eſtates, honouring them with many Offices and Dignities, counting eſpecially their Friendſhip above all others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59120:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. IVX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> being in peace, his Son Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Guy</hi> was married to fair Lyndamira the Kings Daughter. How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> and his Queen returning to <hi rend="blackletterType">Mambrat</hi> found it beſieged, and how he relieved it; with other matters.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIR <hi>Bevis</hi> and his Confederates, being now in peace and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, King <hi>Edgar</hi> ſent for them to his Court, upon a great Feaſt he made for his Nobles, and entertained them with much ſplendor, and a Tilt and Tournament for their fvrther Recreation being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Miles</hi> Sir <hi>Bevis</hi>'s two Sons maintained it againſt all ſtrangers or other Knights of the Court, and were ſo highly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful, that they unhorſes all that came againſt them: Inſomuch that Sir <hi>Guy</hi> being then in ſilver Armor, with a fair Lady portrayed on his Shield, the beautiful <hi>Lyndamira</hi> Daughter to the King, took ſuch norice of his manly form, proportion of Body and rare atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments beyond, in a manner, the ſtrength of man, that ſhe fell deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately in love with him, of which the young Knight being ignorant, and the Princeſs through exceſs of Modeſty, not willing to diſcover it to any, ſhe fell ſick and in a languiſhing condition, whereat the King being greatly grieved, ſent for his Phyſicians, from all parts of the Land to cure her Malady, who ſoon found it proceeded from a cauſe beyond the power of their Art; and enformed the King, that diſtemper of the fair Princeſs, proceeded from love, who tender of this his only Daughter, preſſed her in all Fatherly mildneſs to let him know the object that occaſioned it, which at firſt ſhe began with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty to refuſe, or rather excuſe. but the King being earneſt herein, ſhe amidſt ſighs, bluſhes and much confuſion, told him it was Sir <hi>Guy.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Queen <hi>Joſian</hi> by this time, being deſirous to return to <hi>Mambrat,</hi> as a place more agreeable to her health, acquainted Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> with her intent, who thereupon reſolved to accompany her again, and leave to Sir <hi>Miles</hi> his younger Son his Inheritance in <hi>England,</hi> hardly could King <hi>Edgar</hi> be perſwaded to part with them, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever finding the Queen ill at eaſe he at length conſented, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed them with many rich preſents, exhorting ſundry of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to accompany them, which they accordingly did; and upon his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59120:32"/> Fathers departure, gave to Sir <hi>Miles</hi> all his places, Offices and Titles of Honour, arriving at <hi>Mambrat,</hi> they found the City ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſieged by <hi>Amphi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on,</hi> a Couſen of the King of <hi>Mambrat;</hi> but the Citizens had made a ſtout reſiſtance, and killed abundance of men in divers ſantes they made, but being now quite wearied out, were at a point to yield; whereupon Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> ſent ſecretly into the City, to acquaint them with his arrival, which put them into no ſmall joy, and greatly raiſed and inſpired their drooping Courages, nor was it long, before he gathered an Army in the Country, and ſent for Souldiers into <hi>Armony,</hi> whereupon more fully to ſignalize his Valour to ſuch Engliſh Noble-men, as came with him, that they might report what they had ſeen in their own Country, mounting upon <hi>Arundel,</hi> and taking his Sword <hi>Morglay</hi> in his hand, he fell like a tempeſt upon the Houſt of the Infidels, beating down, and cutting in pieces all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he reached or came in his way, and ſuch ſlaughter he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>de, that the gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d was covered with blood, and the bodies of the ſlain, to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey <hi>Amph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on</hi> with the ſtrongeſt of his men advanced, and cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed upon Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> who though tired with ſighting, yet encountre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them all, and with a blow laid <hi>Amphiron</hi> dead at his feet, by cleaving his Helmet and Head in ſunder, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his men were ſo diſcouraged, that fearfully ſhrinking together, they at laſt betook themſelves to open flight, leaving their Camp and all its furniture, as a pity to the Conqueror.</p>
               <p>The ſiege removed, the Cittizens opened their Gates, and came out with Inſtruments of Muſick, Songs and great Ioy to welcome Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and his Train, who entred the City in Triumph, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed himſelf in the Throne of <hi>Mambrat,</hi> where giving large Preſents to the Engliſh Noble-men, he ſent them back, ſo many as would go into <hi>England;</hi> who came home full of the glorious Actions and Atchievements of Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> ſpeading yet wider his fame that had already render him a moſt redoubted Champion amongſt the Infidels: Inſomuch that <hi>Saracon,</hi> the great Soldian of <hi>Babylon,</hi> hearing of his proweſs, and how by new Conqueſts he dayly inlarged his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, began to doubt his Empire, for the indignities of he had put upon Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> and therefore conſulting his great Councellors it was agreed amongſt them, that they ſhould enterprize ſome extraordinary matter to put a ſtop to the progreſs of his Arms.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:59120:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. VXV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> overthrew the Soldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n of <hi rend="blackletterType">Babylons</hi> Army, that came to diſpoſſeſs him of his Country; Killed <hi rend="blackletterType">Amphiron</hi> their General: And purſued them with great ſlaughter to the City, &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SIR <hi>Bevis</hi> being ſetled in a Kingdom far from his Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and being well aſſured his Neighbours bore him no good will, having ſworn his Subjects to be true to him and his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, he proceeded to make wholeſome Laws, the better to aſſure their fidelity, oblieging them every where to forſake their Idols and falſe worſhip, and to become Chriſtians, but ſcarce had he brought theſe things to paſs, when news was brought him, that great preparations were making to invade his Country, which made him not idle, but taking the advantage of the little reſpire: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gathered his Forces and muſtered them to the number of twenty thouſand men, Horſe and Foot, with which he marched to the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ers, to ſtand u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on his guard: when <hi>Amphiron</hi> whom the Soldian had made his General, advanced by ſpeedy marches, with an Army of two hundred thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Saracens,</hi> vowing the bloodieſt revenge, that could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed or ſuffered by man upon Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> nor only for the diſgrace he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon himſelf ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he had given his Kinſ-man, but the diſgrace he had put upon him, for indeed though he was a monſterous Giant Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> had overthrown him in the head of his Troops and gave him in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>y c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>el wounds, and had diſpatched him, had not his men deſperately to ſave th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, thrown them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves between him and death, whilſt he made his eſcape.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amphiron</hi> by this time doing arrived upon the Confine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brat,</hi> with his numerous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>aſt, began in a terrible manner to waſt all with fire and ſword, ſo that the miſerable Inhabitants fled before them in a fearful manner, to ſtay which inundation of the barbarous Enemy, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> advanced with his Troops, and falling with five hundred Horſe only upon the ſorerunners, conſiſting of ten thouſand men, he made of them ſuch a terrible ſlaughter, that ſuch as eſcaped the ſword leaped into the River for fear, and there were moſt of them drowned not above an hundred eſcaping to teſt <hi>Amphiron</hi> the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59120:33"/> fatal news, who was ſo enraged, that having charged them with Cowardize, he cauſed the chief of them, or ſuch as were Officers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them to be put to death, and ſo came furiouſly on, where Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> had drawn up his whole Army, and now the Armies being in ſight of each other, though the Infidels with their numerous Hoaſt covered the Country Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> nothing daunted, incouraged his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with this ſhort Oration: <hi>You ſee, Fellow Souldier,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and what is yet more glorious, Fellow Chriſtians, that this numerous Hoaſt of Infidels, that defy the bleſſed name of our Lord, and whoſe Armies we have ſo often bafled and defeated, are come up againſt us to deſtroy us, and take away the Land we ſo quietly poſſeſs, and which by right of war and heritage is our own; wherefore be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant for the truth, and let us this day ſo well play the men, in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth our utmoſt proweſs, that hereafter our names may become ſo terrible to them, that they may rather implore our Friendſhip, and become our Tributaries, than dare to arm againſt us, and as for my part, my fear is ſo little, that I doubt not, but this day we ſhall ſo deal, that few of them ſhall eſcape our hands.</hi> This ſpeech ended with ſhouts and acclamations of the Souldiers, he commanded the Trumpets to ſound the Charge; and <hi>Amphiron</hi> having on the other hand encouraged his men, with great boaſts and hopes of aſſured Victory, both Armies joyned with huge ſhouts and cryes, ſo that for the horrible claſhing of Swords and Armour, the cryes of the dying, and the ſhouts of the vanquiſhers, the ſound of Trumpets, and the noiſe of Drums, the Earth trembled, and the wild beaſt in the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts ſtood aſtoniſhed, when <hi>Amphiron</hi> having in his hand a huge Battle-Ax, came on in the front making lanes as he paſſed, ſo that that the Chriſtians ſeeing the deſtruction he made, fled on that part, of which Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> had no ſooner notice where he fought, and had broken the left Wing of the Pagan Army, having died himſelf in the blood of a thouſand he had ſlain, but beating down all before him, he made thither, which <hi>Amphiron,</hi> perceiving by the Banner that was born before him, which was a huge Croſs enameld and inlayed with Gold, but chooſing a thouſand of his beſt men, he gave them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to incloſe Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> on all parts, and that when they had done it, he himſelf would either take him priſoner, or kill him on the place: Theſe men ſpeedily drew off, to fulfil the pleaſure of their General, who had promiſed them great Rewards, if they performed it, and threatned them with certain death, if they were found wanting
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59120:33"/> in the fulfilling his commands to the utmoſt of their power: Vpon this, diſperately reſolved, whilſt Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> was making a lane before him, and paving his way with the bodies of the Infidels, whilſt ſome preſented themſelves before him to ſtop his approach, others fetching a little compaſs incloſed him, and preſſed on very furiouſly, by this means, they had ſeparated him from the body of his Army, which he however not regarding, though many of his men were ſlain about him, with his Sword <hi>Morglay,</hi> made the Arms, Legs and Heads of thoſe that oppoſed him to fly, ſo that <hi>Amphiron</hi> was oblieged to haſten, when, to give him entrance, his men opened to the right and leſt, and he having in a great rage reproached Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> with the taking King <hi>Jours</hi> Queen and Country from him, as alſo impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, he, before Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> could well ward the blow, gave him ſuch a ſtroak with his Battle-Ax, as made him almoſt tumble from his Horſe, but he ſoon recovering himſelf, returned it with ſuch fury, that his truſty Sword peirced <hi>Amphiron</hi>'s Armour, and gave him a deep wound in the Shoulder, ſo that renewing their ſtrength, and either doing his utmoſt, a mortal battel happened between them, but at length, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> his men ſuppoſing him to be in greater danger than he was, after an obſtenate manner, broke in, but ere they came to him, he had with a full ſtroak cleft <hi>Amphiron</hi>'s Head and Helmet, ſo that he fell dead at his Feet; which his men ſeeing, gave back on all hands, and from a kind of a Retreat, finding themſelves ſlain on every ſide: and now Sir <hi>Miles</hi> coming in with five thouſand freſhmen, which he had raiſed unknown to his Father, and beating down all before him, they fell into a confuſed flight, ſo that being hotly purſued to the Walls of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they were almoſt all of them ſlain, drowned, or taken Priſoners.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:59120:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Bevis</hi> beſieged <hi>Babylon,</hi> and how Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Miles,</hi> with a party of Souldiers in diſguiſe, entring the City, was forced to betake himſelf to a Tower; and how the <hi rend="blackletterType">Soldians</hi> Daughter fell in love with him; and how the City was taken.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure/>
               <p>UPon the defeat of this great Army, the City of <hi>Babylon</hi> was filled with the lamentations and cryes of ſuch as had loſt their Friends, and others that feared the City would be ſack'd, for now the Chriſtian Army approached, ſpreading their Banners before the palace, which oblieged the Soldian to conſult, what was beſt to be done for his ſafety; ſome adviſing him to ſend Ambaſſadours with Preſents, and offers of Peace to the Conqueror, and others to ſtand it out,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59120:34"/> ſeeing he had a well fortified City, and many Friends; but ſo it happened, that whilſt they were thus wavering, that King <hi>Jour</hi> having, by corrupting his keepers, made his eſcape, came in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe to <hi>Babylon,</hi> earneſtly ſoliciting the Soldian to maintain a War to the utmoſt againſt his mortal Enemy, whereupon the defence was reſolved upon the Soldian committing to this King the Charge and Guard of the City; ſo that many Aſſaults were given, and many ſore conflicts happened, in the ſallying of the Beſieged, but the City being ſtrongly walled and fortefied with Towers, incloſed on moſt parts with the branches of the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> it could not be eaſily approached, which made Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> conclude how one way or other he might take it by Stratagem, and after many conſultations it was reſolved, that divers armed men, with Pilgrims gowns over their Armour, the better to prevent ſuſpition, ſhould enter the City, and ſecure one of the Gates to let in the reſt of the Army; but then ſome difficulty aroſe, who ſhould enterpriſe this dangerous under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> though he offered it, not being permitted by his Captains, and great Commanders, to undertake ſo dangerous an Enterpriſe, but utterly perſwaded from it, forasmuch as upon his ſafety depended not only the preſervation of the Army, but the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and conſervation of the whole Affairs in thoſe parts; and although he vehemently preſſed it, and deſired nothing more, than to have the honour of ſo great an undertaking, yet againſt all he could argue, the intreaties and perſwaſions of his Friends prevailed; yet not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to looſe the glory, he ſo far prevailed, that Sir <hi>Miles</hi> his Son ſhould attempt it, when not to loſe time, all things were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in a readineſs, and they to the number of two hundred, went to the City hy degrees, and in the night time taking their opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, put the Warders to flight, killing many of them, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves of the principal Gate, but the Alarm being taken, they every where cryed to Arms, ſo that before Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> could well reach it with his Army, Sir <hi>Miles</hi> and his men, after having maintained a furious and obſtenate fight with the whole power of the City, found themſelves obliged to retire to one of the Towers, which in the confuſion was almoſt deſerted of the Souldiers that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore guarded it, putting ſuch as they found there to the Sword, and fortefying themſelves therein, during which time the Portculliſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing let down, and the Gate again ſtrengthened, though Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> and his men attempted to force the Gate and Wall, with battering
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59120:35"/> Rams and other Engins, yet by reaſon of their ſtrength, and the ſtout defence the beſieged made, they could not effect it, which troubled Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> much, but more the fair <hi>Joſian,</hi> who by this time was come to the Camp, as concluding, that paſt all peradventure, Sir <hi>Miles</hi> and his men were either taken Priſoners or ſlain.</p>
               <p>During the ſorrow the Chriſtian Camp made for this ſuppoſed loſs and miſcariage, the Soldian had ſtrictly cauſed the Tower to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, which King <hi>Jour</hi> who had the conduct of this affair, preſſed on with great vehemency, and was frequently as obſtinately repulled, when in the hight of this Action it ſo happened, that the fair and beautiful <hi>Roſalinda</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and only Daughter to the Soldian, dreamed ſhe ſaw Sir <hi>Miles,</hi> or the Imagined Idea of that Heroick young Knight by her bed-ſide, with whoſe feacures ſhe was ſo wonderfully taken, as alſo with his manly proportion and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial looks, that ſhe could not forbear to fix her Eyes upon him, and demand what his requeſt or deſire was, or what brought him thither, who returned for anſwer, that her beauty alone had charmed him, and that although at preſent he was beſet with danger, yet no fear poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed him, no not twice the number of his Enemies, but the fear of her frowns alone could ſhake his ſoul, upon which ſeeming to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apear with a ſigh and much diſcontent ſhe awaked and was ſo affected with the Viſion, though ſhe found it to be nothing elſe, that ſhe could not blot it out of her memory, but ſtill fancied the manly ſhape be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Eyes, and ſo far it wrought with her paſſion, and affection, that ſhe became reſtleſs; when ſtanding one day to behold the Aſſault of the Tower, and perceiving a gallant Youth armed at all points with a Cask of Gold adorned with a Plume of crimſon Feathers on his Head, ſhe verely conceited him to be the ſame ſhe had ſeen in the Viſion, and from that time, uſed her endeavours with her Father to offer honourable conditions to thoſe that were beſieged in the Tower, telling him it would be the only means to obliege the Commanders of the Chriſtian Army to raiſe the Siege, but finding him inflexible, and Love prompting her on, ſhe adventured with two Knights, whom her Bounty had made her Creatures, and two of her Maids of Honour, under the favour of the night, to find admittance into the Tower, ſo powerful is Love, that it takes the Diadems from Queens, and with ſome difficulty obtained it; when being brought to Sir <hi>Miles,</hi> and ſhe perceiving him to be the very ſame her fancy had repreſented, ſhe ſtood in a manner tranſported, which the courteous Knight per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59120:35"/> and ſeeing ſo excellent a beauty before him, fell at her feet, and with profound reverence kiſſed her fair hand, who raiſing him ſaid, Ah my Lord, why do you ſhew this reſpect to your Captive, who though a Princeſs is nevertheleſs conſtrained. (O pardon my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, for this freedome, contrary to the rules of our Ser,) to beg a ſavour, I hope, is in your power to give, and look not upon it, as the effects of my preſumption, but the effects of Love, and it is your Love I ask, and for which I have not only undertaken this difficulty, but put my ſelf into the power of my Fathers Enemy, hazarding what ever the World may conſtrue of my reputation. At this the young Knight ſtood more and more amazed, telling her that in the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he was in, he was no ways able to render a returne ſuitab e to her greatneſs, much more to her affection, and thus they diſcourſed, ſtriving to out do each other in Generoſitie, the Princeſs offering not only to turn Chriſtian upon this conſideration, but to ſacrifice her life-to her Fathers Indignation, if no leſs would ſatisfie him on his be half, and he proteſted rather to looſe his own life, than ſuffer her to run the leaſt danger or hazard, when in the mean time King <hi>Jour</hi> and the Captains under his command, prepared to ſtorm the Bulwarks of the Tower, being impatient to have a Foe both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without at one and the ſame time, ſo that having drawn thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a great ſtrength with Engins, Ropes and ſcaling Ladders with great eryes they gave a furious onſet, upon which the fair <hi>Roſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linda</hi> in hopes her preſence might ſtay the aſſayling Souldiers, whilſt Sir <hi>Miles</hi> was ſetting his men in order, ſhe appeared upon the Walls, and exhorted them to retire, who although they knew her, regarded not her voice at that time, but at the inſtigation of King <hi>Jour,</hi> were the rather inraged, who ſupoſed, they had taken the Princeſs Priſoner, and kept her there, as a miſerable Captive; ſo that break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the out-works, and aſcending by degrees, crying out to the Souldiers, that if they intended to have any Quarter, or ſave their lives, they ſhould inſtantly deliver up Sir <hi>Miles,</hi> and the place pouring at the ſame time ſhowers of Arrows, one of which ſlightly wounded the fair <hi>Roſalinda</hi> in the ſhoulder, ſo that the bloud trickled down her ſnowy Breaſts, which Sir <hi>Miles</hi> perceiving, and having cauſed her to retire out of danger, committing her to the hands of her Maids for cure, in a great fury he threw open the Gates, and with his Sword in his hand cryed to thoſe that preſſed on, Behold <hi>Miles,</hi> behold the man you ſeek is here, to dare your vengance, and with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59120:36"/> that, leaping forward with an invincible Courage, in ſpite of all the reſiſtance they made, he covered the ſteps of the aſcent with the bodies of the ſlain, and being backed with thoſe few Men he had left, fought with unwearied Vigor and Courage, killing all that ſtood in his way, when to prevent the ſlaughter, King <hi>Jour</hi> approached with dreadful threatnings and imprecations to revenge the affronts the Father had done him, upon the Son between whom began a mortal Battle, which concluded with the death of the King, and that ſo diſheartned the Souldiers, that they gave back, of which the Soldian having notice, and that his beloved Daughter was in the hands of his Enemy, he came thither with all his power, ſo that the fight grew exceeding hot, which Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> who was again advanced to the Walls, perceiving by the crys, though he knew not of certainly that Sir <hi>Miles</hi> was alive, at a venture reſolved to hazard the utmoſt to enter the City, wherein he was ſo ſucceſsful, that paſſing the River at an unſuſpected place, he with his battering Rams beat down a part of the Wall, at which breach he entred and ſo unexpectedly ſet upon the Soldian, that he overthrew his people by Squadrens, cutting in pieces all that came in his way, whilſt Sir <hi>Miles</hi> fighting on the other ſide, drove them upon his Sword, which piteous plight, of his diſtreſed Citizens, the Soldian perceiving, and that all was in a likelyhood to be loſt, he with the Troops of his Guards, and the truſty of his Followers, retired to the pallace leaving the reſt to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who were miſerably ſlain and beaten down, till throwing away their Weapons, they fell on their Knees, and beged mercy, whereupon, at the intreaty of the Princeſs, their lives were ſpared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:59120:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the Pallace was beſieged. How fair <hi rend="blackletterType">Roſalinda</hi> grew diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, for her diſobedience to her Father. The Letter ſhe ſent him, and the Anſwer ſhe received. The grief Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Miles</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at her abſence, and upon finding her undertook to conclude a Peace.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure/>
               <p>ALthough Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> had entred and poſſeſſed himſelf of the City, yet the Pallace being ſtrongly fortified with Ditches, Walls, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and Rampiers, and in it above twelve thouſand men, there being no way of eaſy acceſs to it, but by a Bridge, it cauſed him to girt it ſtrictly with a cloſe Siege, and threw into it, Wildfire, Stones, and Arrows, which greatly indamaged the beſieged, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59120:37"/> the Soldian, though ſummoned remained obſtinate not being willing to liſten to any accord, but cauſed his men to ſally in parties as he ſaw occaſion, in which many of them were cut off.</p>
               <p>Whilſt theſe things paſſed, the ardent Affections increaſed between Sir <hi>Miles</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Roſilinda,</hi> he uſing all manner of dil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and good carriage to her to obliege her, who notwithſtanding became ſad through the callamity, that threatned her Father and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Relations, as alſo for the great effuſion of bloud that had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the City, and eſpecially upon her occaſion, and finding no hopes of ſeeing her Father without a Reconciliation, ſhe ſtudied how ſhe might be inſtrumental in making a laſting Peace, and yet ſecure her ſelf in the poſſeſſion of her Lover, whereupon with only one of her Maids appointed to wait upon her, ſhe retired from the noiſe and clamour of War, to a private receſs, and taking pen, ink and paaper, wrote the following Letter.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>MOST Mighty Soldian, Emperor of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and my honoured Father, How but with Bluſhes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, can your diſobedient Daughter, frame her ſelf to write unto you, who in a time of danger, has delivered her ſelf into the hands of your Enemies; But Dread Sir, when you ſhall know that what I have done, proceeded from an extraordinary Affection, a Love ſurpaſſing the bounds of Reaſon, and even of Duty it ſelf: I hope Dread Sir, You will take compaſſion upon a diſtreſſed Maid, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in many afflictions, and out of the abundance of tenderneſs and fatherly compaſſion, paſs over this one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience in her, who has ever made it her ſtudy to obey and Reverence you, and ſtill is ready to ſacrifice her life to your diſpleaſure, to expiate ſo great an offence, but muſt lowly beg pardon, if ſhe cannot forgoe the powerful Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, even in death, which has chained her to ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous an Enemy, who wiſhes nothing more than your ſafety and happineſs; therefore, deareſt Father, If the Tears or Intreaties of your afflicted Daughter, may find any place in your Breaſt, regard your own ſafety and the life and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59120:37"/> of her who but in the caſe of Love, could have been guilty of an Act of Diſobedience, and hearken to the offer of Peace, that will ſhortly be propoſed to you, in hopes this Letter may work upon you in ſome meaſure to mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate your diſpleaſure, and diſpoſe you to imbrace as Friends, thoſe you now hold your Enemies; I remain,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Dread Sir,</salute>
                        <signed>Your afflicted Daughter <hi>ROSALINDA.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Letter ſhe ſent by her Maid, who by a private known way, got into the City; when in the mean while ſhe continued penſive, in expectation of the event, but Sir <hi>Miles</hi> returning from beating the Soldians men, that had ſallied, into the Pallace, dy'd with blood and ſlaughter, and miſſing fair <hi>Roſalinda,</hi> whom he had left in his Tent, he made ſtrict enquiry after her, but none being able to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie him herein, between Love and Anger, he ſtood for a while mute not knowing what to do, or what to determine, one while he ſuppoſed this fair Creature came as a Spy to betray him to her Fathers power, during his being incloſed in the Caſtle, but then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the hazard and danger ſhe run, upon enterprizing ſuch a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, ſuch low thoughts were daſhed, and he concluded that nothing but an extraordinary paſſion could obliege her to it, blaming himſelf for having any ſuch thought of ſo much innocence and goodneſs, and thereupon ſent through the City in ſearch of her, but the Meſſengers returning without any news, our young Knight concluded, ſhe had ſecretly withdrawn her ſelf into the Pallace, and upon ſecond thoughts caſt her ſelf at her Fathers feet, to implore his pardon for her Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and ſo bereft him of all his hopes of happineſs, whereupon he began to accuſe Fortune, for flattering him with ſo glorious a proſpect of felicity, and then ſo ſuddainly to caſt a cloud or veil over it, and leave him in darkneſs and diſpair, and ſo much the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance increaſed that his mind began to be in diſorder.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:59120:38"/>
               <p>Thus whilſt Sir <hi>Miles</hi> was grieving for the fair Princeſs, the Maid returned, having delivered the Letter that was given her in charge, with this anſwer from the Soldian: That it could never before enter into his thoughts that a Daughter of ſuch tender regard could prove diſobedient to her Father, who had ſo highly cheriſhed her, and prepared a Neighbour King to be her Husband, but ſince ſhe no more regarded her duty, nor honour than to deſert him, and baſely caſt her ſelf into the Arms of his Enemy unſought, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps altogether unwelcome, he from that time utterly renounced her, nor did he any longer conſider her as his Daughter, but rather as one transformed into an unnatural Monſter, to conſpire to deſtroy thoſe that gave her life, under a pretence of Love, however her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions to peace wrought ſo little on him, that he was reſolved to continue a War to the laſt extremity, not doubting but he ſhould have powerful Aids come to his Reſcue, not being yet ſo low ſunk by one misfortune, but he had yet remaining many Friends. At this ſharp reply, the fair Princeſs fell in a ſound, and when ſhe was by the help of her Maid recovered, ſhe very much bewailed and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented her hard fortune, that if ſhe muſt be obedient, ſhe muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go her love; and if ſhe retained her love, ſhe muſt remain diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient: but whilſt ſhe was in this agony, and in a manner ſtraitned to know what ſhe ſhould determine, Sir <hi>Miles</hi> who had ſearched all places for his fair Princeſs, hearing ſome body ſigh in that melancholy and lowly cell, where ſhe ſat to bewail her difficulty between love and obedience, he entred, where to his great Ioy he found her in that diſconſolate condition and tenderly embracing her with a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Ioy, demanded the cauſe why ſhe had abſented her ſelf to put him into ſo much fear and perplexity, who thereupon told him whatever had paſſed, entreating him to uſe his utmoſt diligence to make a peace, and perſwade his Father to offer honourable terms, which he promiſed to do, when having kiſſed her fair hand, he took his leave and haſted to the Army, where he found the Ditches fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up with earth and faggots, the ſcaling ladders and wildfires with all other things prepared for the Aſſault, and nothing wanting but the ſignal to be given, whereupon he went to Sir <hi>Bevis,</hi> and implored him, that for his ſake, the pallace might be ſummoned, and peace offered intreating, that himſelf might make the propoſals, which he doubted not but would be accepted, and prove ſuch as would of Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies make them laſting Friends, which being put into his power to do,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59120:38"/> he immediatly ſent a Trumpet with ſeveral Articles, which will be mentioned in the next Chapter, giving the Soldian a days time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How a peace was concluded upon the Soldian, and his people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Chriſtians, and marrying his Daughter to Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Miles</hi> with his Dominion as a Dower after his deceaſe. How Sir <hi rend="blackletterType">Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis</hi> and his Queen died, and what was remarkable in their pious end.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure/>
               <p>During theſe tranſactions, the Chriſtians that inhabited the <hi>Holy Land</hi> were grievouſly oppreſſed by the Infidels, who not only loaded them with grievous Taxes, but took their Children from them, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59120:39"/> forcibly oblieged them to embrace the Mahomitan Superſtition, and frequently puniſhing ſuch as refuſed a complyance with exceeding ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, ſo that many of them died under the torments to which they were put, and by reaſon of this cruel uſage, many of them grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a manner weary of their lives, they at laſt, upon notice of Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> his great proweſs and extraordinary ſucceſs, ſent to him Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters full of lamentation, advertizing him, how they were made the ſcorn and Reproach of the Enemies of Chriſtianity humbly imploring him to reſcue them out of the hands of their Adverſaries, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon calling together his Friends, adviſed with them what was to be done in ſo weighty an affair; who after mature diliberation, told him, that ſince Heaven had ſo ſignally proſpered his undertakings, he ſhould not neglect ſo good a work, as to ſuccor and relieve his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Fellow Chriſtians, whereupon he raiſed an Army of forty thouſand men, and taking leave of his Queen, paſſed into <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ine,</hi> and there after a bloudy and obſtinate fight, overthrew an Army of 200000 Turks and Sarazens, who were gathered to oppoſe his paſſage; upon which bloody overthrow, moſt of the Towns yielded at the firſt ſummons, and thoſe that held out were obliged to do it by compulſion; ſo that making himſelf intire Maſter of the Country, he reſtored thoſe places to the Chriſtians, that had been forcibly taken from them, and acted ſuch prodigious wonders in Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, that his name grew terrible to the Infidels, who ſued for Peace, and in order to obtain it, ſent their Ambaſſadors with great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, proteſting not only to live peaceably with the Chriſtians, but to hold the Country tributary of him, which ſubmiſſion being accepted, he le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſtrong Garriſons in the moſt important places, and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Patriarch of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to have the ſupream Command under him, he returned to his Kingdom with great Triumph and Applauſe.</p>
               <p>By this time Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> grown in years, and having ſpent much time in War and B oodſhed, promoting what in him lay, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion and delivering the oppreſſed Chriſtians from the Turks and Sarazens Tyrany, he betook himſelf and his Queen to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Life ſending for Sir <hi>Guy</hi> to ſucceed him in his Dominion, bequeathing all his poſſeſſions in <hi>England</hi> to Sir <hi>Terry,</hi> Son to Sir <hi>Sabre</hi> now deceaſed; when falling ſick with his Queen, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Sons before him, and having eſtabliſhed them in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of thoſe Kingdoms he had gained, he enjoyned them on his bleſſing to carry his, and his Queens Body, when they ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59120:40"/> to die, to <hi>Southampton,</hi> and there inter them in one Tomb, which was accordingly obſerved, with great Solemnity and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, their Epitaph being this:</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="epitaph">
                  <body>
                     <head>The EPITAPH.</head>
                     <l>Valour and Beauty in this Marble lies,</l>
                     <l>The valiant, fair, the chaſt, the good, the wiſe;</l>
                     <l>The matchleſs <hi>Bevis</hi> and his Queen lye here,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe worthy Fame the World has every where.</l>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And thus, Reader, have I concluded the famous Hiſtory of Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> who for his worthy Exploits, and great Actions may be juſtly ranked with the beſt Champions of Chriſtendom.</p>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>FINIS.</hi>
                  <figure/>
               </trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59120:40"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for, and are to be ſold by <hi>W. Thackeray</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Duck-Lane.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>SIR <hi>John Hawkwood</hi> or the Hiſtory of the <hi>Merchant-Taylors.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Speedy Poſt with a Packet of Letters.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tom a Lincoln,</hi> or the Red-Roſe Knight.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Palmerin</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in three parts.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Montelion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of the Gentle Craft.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> Engliſh.</item>
               <item>Dream of <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Dives.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Dutch</hi> Fortune-Teller.</item>
               <item>The third Part of the Seven Champions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jack</hi> of <hi>Newbery.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scoggin</hi>'s Jeſts.</item>
               <item>Royal Arbour.</item>
               <item>The Book of Knowledge of things unknown.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Markham</hi>'s faithful Farrier.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Markham</hi>'s Method.</item>
               <item>Garland of Delight.</item>
               <item>Crown Garland.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robin Hood</hi>'s Garland.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mucedorus,</hi> a Play.</item>
               <item>Arcandam, or the Famous Aſtrologian.</item>
               <item>Sport and Paſtime</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Ornatus</hi> and <hi>Arteſia.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59120:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS</hi> Printed for, and are to be ſold by <hi>J. Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Gilt-Spur-Street</hi> without <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Triumphant Weaver; or, The Art of Weaving, in Verſe, in 4to.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Dutch</hi> Fortune-Teller.</item>
               <item>The third Part of the Seven Champions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Markham</hi>'s faithful Farrier.</item>
               <item>Arcandam, or the famous Aſtrologian.</item>
               <item>Sport and Paſtime.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Ornatus</hi> and <hi>Arteſia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The noble birth and adventures of <hi>Robin Hood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wiſdoms Cabinet opened; or, The Seaven Wiſe Maſters of <hi>Rome,</hi> in 4to.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of the Seven Champions.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Bevis</hi> of <hi>Southampton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Heavenly Paſſenger, or the Pilgrim's Progreſs, in Verſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hocus Pocus,</hi> or the Art of Jugling.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Fortunatus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The life and death of <hi>Sheffery ap Morgan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The loyal Garland of Mirth and Paſtime; to which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Bell-man</hi>'s loyal Verſes.</item>
               <item>A Groatſworth of Wit for a penny, or the interpretation of Dreams.</item>
               <item>The true Tryal of Underſtanding; Or, Wit newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived: Being a Book of Excellent New Riddles. Very pleaſant and delightful to read.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>At the afore-mentioned places, any</hi> Country-Chapmen <hi>or others, may be furniſhed with all ſorts of ſmall</hi> Books, Broadſides <hi>and</hi> Ballads <hi>at very reaſonable Rates.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:59120:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
